<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ægyptian courtier Delivered in two sermons, before the Vniversitie, at St. Maries Church in Oxford. The first, Iuly 25. 1631. The other, Iuly 6. 1634. By Richard Thornton, Mr. of Arts, and sometimes fellow of Lincolne Colledge.</title>
            <author>Thornton, Richard, Fellow of Lincoln College.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104630</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840363</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840363</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4863</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13747)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4863)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 862:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Ægyptian courtier Delivered in two sermons, before the Vniversitie, at St. Maries Church in Oxford. The first, Iuly 25. 1631. The other, Iuly 6. 1634. By Richard Thornton, Mr. of Arts, and sometimes fellow of Lincolne Colledge.</title>
                  <author>Thornton, Richard, Fellow of Lincoln College.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. P[urslowe] for Henry Seile, and are to be sold at the Tygres head in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The second sermon has a separate title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4863:1"/>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:4863:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:4863:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4863:2"/>
            <p>THE AEGYPTIAN COVRTIER.</p>
            <p>Delivered in two Sermons, before the Vniv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſitie, at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARIES Church in <hi>Oxford.</hi> The firſt, Iuly 25. 1631. The other, Iuly 6. 1634.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> RICHARD THORNTON, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Arts, and ſometimes Fellow of</hi> LINCOLNE COLLEDGE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ERASM. ENCHIR.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Habet unumquodque vitae genus cognata quaedam degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi pericula; ca qui commonstrat, non derogat ordini, ſed rem ordinis agit.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLVS. 8. VER. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Deſpiſe not the diſcourſe of the wiſe, but acquaint thy ſelfe with their Proverbs: for of them thou ſhalt learne inſtruction, and how to ſerve great men with eaſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E. P.</hi> for HENRY SEILE, and are to be ſold at the Tygres head in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4863:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4863:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a great queſtion, whether Art or Nature be more fruitfull, in produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Monſters: the one, preſents many erroneous and wilfull opinions; the other wanders up and downe in many groſſe deformities and corruptions of life; both, active and forward enough to publiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, did not the power of Heaven, the wiſedome of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, reſtraine them both. But paſſing along the channels of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> once the Nurſerie of Learning, famous for varietie and abundance of ſuch Prodigies; I finde one, of one kinde, as chiefe for his qualitie, as for his Office; one, in whom concurre the aberrations of Art and Nature; one complying with each of them, to make himſelfe one of both, a ſtrange prodigious Monſter, <hi>a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man without bowels,</hi> a man-pleaſer, yet no friend: ſuch a man, of whom there can be no Picture drawne, no full expreſſion, unleſse we goe againe to <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> for ſome new invention of Paper and Characters: Time (perhaps) may hereafter diſcover him in better colours; in the meane while, who liſt may come and ſee, and learne to ſave himſelfe from this untoward gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4863:4"/>
            <p>The Story is a Looking-Glaſse, wherein moſt paſſengers may ſee a glimpſe of themſelves, either acting or ſuffring affliction; here you may gueſſe at the ſubſtance, by the ſhadow: and if the boundleſse waters of trouble (ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the height of a Proverbe) have made it tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent enough for each man (whom it may concerne) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect a little upon himſelfe; thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upon the River <hi>Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> the place from whence it came, whoſe overflowings makes the ſoyle thus fruitfull, beneficiall to all.</p>
            <p>How-ever, be it never ſo meane a Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dtie put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Marchant (like <hi>Ioſeph</hi> himſelfe, no better eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by his owne brethren) and bought at firſt by <hi>Iſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> men of the meaner ſort; yet in time, the price thereof may be rayſed by experience, and ſo made good for great ones: ſure I am (like a Glaſſe indeed) there is matter in it which hath beene tryed in the fire, and which returnes impreſſion, without flatterie.</p>
            <p>The Worke (in plaine tearmes) is a Rod prepared for the backe of fooles; but yet (like that of <hi>Moſes</hi>) ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched onely over the Land of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> no wiſe man will be offended, nor any true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> in whom there is no guile. The God of all conſolation (who turned a Rod into a Serpent, and made a Serpent wiſe by nature, for a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of instruction) proſper my weake endeavours, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove theſe Bloſsomes to maturitie, that his bleſſed Name may be glorified, the Church edified, <hi>Ioſephs</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions remembred, his enemies ſcattered, his friends encreaſed, all of us wiſer unto ſalvation, and my ſelfe every day more profitably</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, R. THORNTON.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an <hi>in</hi> Lincolnſhire, <date>
                     <hi>April the 4. 1635.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4863:4"/>
                  <head>THE AEGYPTIAN COVRTIER. <hi>The first Sermon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>GEN. 40. VER. 23.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Yet did not the chiefe Butler remember <hi>IOSEPH,</hi> but forgot hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE way to true happineſſe, is but a troubleſome pilgrimage, diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with varietie of by-paths, wherein temptations on every ſide lye at catch, like ſo many rubs and ſhrubs, both obſcuring and diſturbing the paſſage: So that <hi>a Houſe of Bordage</hi> muſt be inhabited, before <hi>a Land of Promiſe;</hi> and hee who will not paſſe through a Wilderneſſe of hunger and thirſt, ſhall never come into that pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſant Land, flowing with Milke and Honey. He who thinkes to goe to Heaven in a <hi>ſleepe,</hi> ſhall never come there but in a <hi>dreame;</hi> which I am ſure, if <hi>Joſeph</hi> may interprete, will finde no anſwer of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4863:5"/> peace. No; his experience proves the contrarie: <hi>the Irons entred into his ſoule,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.18.</note> before the Veſtments of fine Linnen came neere his body;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.42.3.</note> even thoſe Iron fetters hurt his feet, before the <hi>Gold Ring</hi> did beautifie his hand, or the <hi>Chaine</hi> his necke: before others did bow the knee to him, he bowed the knee to others; to his <hi>brethren,</hi> for compaſſion; to his <hi>Maſter, Potiphar,</hi> for juſtice; to his <hi>fellow</hi> in the Dungeon, for favour: His <hi>brethren</hi> were bound to commiſerate the anguiſh of his ſoule, by the Law of Nature, the Nature of fraternitie; and yet they ſold him for a ſlave to the <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.28.</note> and made the benefit of a Brother, but the commoditie of a Merchant: His <hi>Maſter</hi> was bound to doe him right at leaſt, for the fidelitie of his ſervice; a ſervice very proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.20.</note> and yet he put him in priſon: His <hi>fellow priſoner</hi> was bound to remember the truth of his interpretation; an interpretation very welcome, bringing glad tidings, tidings of deliverance, and reſtitution to his place: <hi>Yet did not the chiefe Butler, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The meaning of which words, preſents unto us <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> forgot by an <hi>Aegyptian Courtier:</hi> And becauſe the want of remembrance in theſe dayes is but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fault, ſometimes an excuſe, alwayes moſt lyable to exception from the qualitie of the parties; the buſineſſe in hand will ſeeme no matter of importance, unleſſe wee enter into the conſideration of theſe two particulars (as generall parts) <hi>Ioſephs</hi> condition, and the <hi>chiefe Butlers;</hi> both which are the ſtory and premiſſes of this Chapter, whereof my Text is the concluſion: In <hi>Ioſephs</hi> condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you may ſee the motives of remembrance; in the <hi>chiefe Butlers</hi> condition, you may gueſſe at the reaſons of his forgetfulneſſe: Theſe motives, thoſe reaſons arguing his unworthineſſe to be a friend to any, much leſſe a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to his Prince, not ſo much deſerving a good turne as a bad one, rather the chiefe Bakers fate, than the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans imitation; and ſo I proceed in the firſt place, to take a view of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> condition, a plaine caſe: <hi>Yet did, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4863:5"/>3 What <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was before his comming into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> will not be much materiall to perſwade reſpect; the World we know eſteemes men by what they are, not as they have beene: Indeed, in a caſe of envie, or revenge, <hi>tenax injuriarum memoria,</hi> the worſt (though paſt) is ſooneſt remembred; but in a caſe of miſerie, the beſt being paſt, is ſoone thought tedious to be heard, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, ſeldome worthy to be beleeved, eſpecially in a man of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> condition: in whom, if it ſtand not with the wiſdome of this great man to beleeve more than he ſaw, yet hee muſt needes take notice of theſe <hi>three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,</hi> to enforce his remembrance afterwards: <hi>firſt,</hi> that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was a <hi>priſoner: ſecondly,</hi> that hee was a man of ſpeciall worth, an <hi>Interpreter: thirdly,</hi> that hee was a <hi>petitioner;</hi> each whereof aggravating the chiefe Butlers unworthineſſe, makes this ſhort Text too long for an houres worke: ſo that it ſeemes beſt, onely to ſpeake of the two former particulars at this time, and leave the Petitioner till hereafter, as fitteſt and moſt likely to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and wait upon this Courtiers condition.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Firſt then, he was a <hi>priſoner.</hi> Whether this was a ſtate of miſerie, or no, the chiefe Butler knew by his owne experience: he once had beene a priſoner, and that in the ſame place; there I am ſure he lookt <hi>ſad, Verſe</hi> 6. and by the loſſe of his Office,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15.</note> wanted that <hi>Wine</hi> which makes glad the heart of man: and (indeed) could hee looke otherwiſe than ſad, in a place of that nature?<note n="*" place="margin">Pareus in Gen.</note> 
                     <hi>Non liberalis cuſtodia ſed faedus carcer è figura rotunda habens deſuper orificium</hi> (as ſome will obſerve from the originall) no free Priſon, but an obſcure ſubterraneous noyſome Vault, of a round figure, with the mouth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; ſignifying (perhaps) that whoſoever comes there) muſt quickly be turn'd upſide downe; libertie, into thraldome; chaines of Gold, into fetters of Iron; Wine, into Water; varietie of delicacies, into bread of affliction: even the freſh aire, which was the cheapeſt, muſt now be the deareſt commoditie; no fortunes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4863:6"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4863:6"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4863:7"/> allowance, to ſupply the wants; no ancient ſervants to attend the perſon, no faithful friends to adviſe the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, no kind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, none at all to come neere the place of a <hi>cloſe priſoner,</hi> who alone ſeems enriched with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of former contents, to aggravate the depth of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t miſerie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. No marvel if he were ſad: <hi>Joſephs</hi> experience was the ſame in proportion to his eſtate, witneſſe <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105. The chiefe Butler knew ſo much, for he was a priſoner at the ſame time with <hi>Joſeph; Joſephs</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llow priſoner. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at that time he had a little more liberty than before, &amp; yet this gave him a fairer way to relate the ſeverity of his former puniſhment: for though <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (being a meane &amp; contemptible man, without friends or fortunes) might heretofore ſeeme unworthy to receive any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>avor, even the favor to be heard fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<note n="*" place="margin">Nec vile pute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur oſſic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um cum apud Reges Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baros u que hodit maximae dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſit Regi pocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum porrigere. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
                     </note> other <hi>Archipincerna,</hi> the chiefe Butler, <hi>primariae dignitatis vir,</hi> a man of the firſt ranke, of greateſt authority in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe; yet now the caſe is altered, they were both priſoners together, the diſparity is growne leſſe, affliction makes the haughty mind ſtoupe; and for want of other, thinks this a content, <hi>ſocios habero doloris,</hi> to have fellow priſoners, partners in affliction: for thus opportunity and patience, to heare men ſpeak in their own behalf, may be obtained without petition or a bribe, and willingly return'd too, by way of requitall. Men being by nature deſirous to eaſe their troubled hearts, ſtrive to mitigate their ſorrow, by imparting it one to another: nay, (being greedy to catch at any ſhadow of reliefe) they ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily comply together in this mutuall preſumption, if one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be releaſed, the other may hope to be remembred.<note n="*" place="margin">Caeterum iis qui in eodem erant carcere quoties labor intermitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> confabulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus (ita ul ſolent) miſeriarum ſocus &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ae damnatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cauſam invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem percontanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus pincerna Regi charus familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem cum fuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it. <hi>Ioſeph, lib. 2. Antio.</hi>
                     </note> Something it was of like nature, which made this great Officer ſo willing to interchange language with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and which made <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſo bold as to ask him a queſtion; what queſtion? a reaſon only, and that no reaſon of State, but a reaſon within the circumference of his own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; the Dungeon, a reaſon of ſadneſſe, a paſſage moſt remarkable of all others, during the time of his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and therefore a little to be obſerved for his better
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4863:7"/> remembrance who forgot it, and yet it ſeemes leaſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of notice: for was it not a ſufficient reaſon of ſadnes, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhut up in ſo unworthy a place? me thinks that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in <hi>Petrarch, carcere claudor indigno,</hi> might wel have begun the dialogue, &amp; prevented the queſtion: but <hi>Joſeph</hi> (by his long acquaintance with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of that place) could have given himſelfe this anſwer, before he moved the queſtion, had he not perceived the ſadnes to be more than ordinary: and therfore, to proceed from a cauſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the effect, this cauſe could not be that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diſcourſe incident to all men in affliction, whereby extremitie and hope and folly beget &amp; increaſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. No,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6.</note> it was <hi>in the morning</hi> (ſaith the Text) before any ſuch diſcourſe was ſtirring, and that not in reſpect of the morning unloſing the ſenſes from ſleep, &amp; thereby expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a more violent apprehenſion of thoſe miſeries whereof the day before they had ſurfeted, for this was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very daies work; but the queſtion was, <hi>Cur triſtior ſolito ſit hodie facies veſtra? Why are ye ſo ſad to day?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7.</note> And if it were in reſpect of ſleepe, judge ye. Indeed the cares of an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed mind having wearied a man in the day tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, may aſſault him in the night by a dreame: thus the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may dreame of his Oxe, &amp; the Mariner of his Sailes; and thus all in a priſon may find it, not only waking, but ſleeping, a place of miſery: but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n this phantaſme quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vaniſheth, <hi>tantummodo creditur dum videtur,</hi> it is belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved only ſo long as it is ſeene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; ſo c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uld not aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rwards be a means of any ſadnes more than ordinary, unleſſe it were more than an ordinary dreame: and if it were more than an ordinary dreame (as indeed it was) the ſadnes, how great ſoever, muſt needs more &amp; more increaſe; for here's none (for ought this great <hi>Aegyptian</hi> knew) that could inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it, anſwera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le to the ſuperſtition of his country, and the greatneſſe of his feares; none but <hi>Ioſeph</hi> not likely to help others, who had bin the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e (even there) ſo long him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; not likely to be an Interpreter, who was a fellow pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and that willing to wait, as their occaſions ſerved.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4863:8"/>
                  <p>And now, if there were no other Remembrancer, but the afflictions of the body, the loſſes of fortunes, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions of the minde, both waking and ſleeping, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all priſoners; how could one forget another? how could one, being releaſed, not remember him who was left behinde? Surely, not by the Law of Nature; for by it one man cannot hurt another: What then? <hi>Lactantius</hi> makes the argument;<note place="margin">L. Fir. Divin. Inſtit. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Si nocere homini contra naturam ſit, prodeſſe igitur homini ſecundum naturam fit neceſſe eſt:</hi> If to hurt a man, be againſt Nature; then ſurely to doe him good, is moſt agreeable to Nature: And though this be one of thoſe precepts which binde alwayes, and at all times; yet the more a mans neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſtands in need of this good, the more the dutie is required.<note place="margin">Sen. in Prover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biis.</note> And therefore <hi>Seneca</hi> goes further; <hi>Qui ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currere perituro poteſt, cum non ſuccurrit, occidit:</hi> He that may helpe a man readie to periſh, and will not, makes himſelfe lyable to that mans deſtruction. The Scripture ſtrikes it home in the 41. <hi>Pſalme:</hi> From whence wee may well conclude,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.1.</note> That he who <hi>regardeth</hi> not <hi>the poore and needie, the Lord will</hi> not <hi>deliver him in the time of trouble:</hi> His want of humanitie, doth not onely damnifie his brother, but makes himſelfe a looſer. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Schoole-men give us <hi>two reaſons,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aq.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 30.2. <hi>C.</hi>
                     </note> why every man ſhould make his neighbours calamitie his owne: Firſt, <hi>propter unionem amoris,</hi> for the love one man muſt beare another; not onely in generall, according to the rules of humanitie, common to Infidels; but more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26. <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.3.</note> as <hi>members</hi> of one body, whereof Chriſt Ieſus is the Head, who made himſelfe <hi>a man of ſorrowes,</hi> for the good of others. And therefore, if there be any of thoſe <hi>Plant-animalia,</hi> Plants having the ſenſe of feeling (as ſome report) in regard if one leafe be cut off, or bruiſed, all the reſt will preſently ſhrinke and contract them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: ſurely they were created for an embleme of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, worthy to be worne upon your heads; but chiefely to be rooted in your hearts, if you deſire to be leaves
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4863:8"/> of that Plant, and branches of that Tree, which is found in the Land of the living, and growes in the Paradiſe of Heaven.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 The other reaſon is, <hi>propter poſſibilitatem ſimilia patiendi,</hi> becauſe man is ſtill in poſſibilitie to endure the like afflictions himſelfe. If rich <hi>Croeſus</hi> could have beene ſecured from change, he and his wealth had never beene enſlaved to <hi>Cyrus.</hi> Was any more eminent than <hi>Nebuchadnezzar?</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Is not this great Babel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan</hi> 4.30.33.</note> 
                     <hi>which I have built for the houſe of the Kingdome, by the might of my power, for the honour of my Majeſtie?</hi> And yet behold hee was forc'd to change his habitation, to have his dwelling amongſt the beaſts of the earth, and for ſeven yeeres together eat graſſe like Oxen, till his haires were growne like Eagles feathers, and his nailes like birds clawes, as it is in the fourth of <hi>Daniel.</hi> Had any more favour amongſt the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> than <hi>David</hi> the Kings ſonne in law? and yet behold hee was forc'd to flye for his life to a neighbour Prince, and to begge his bread of churliſh <hi>Nabal.</hi> Are any more beloved than the Saints and ſervants of God? and yet wee read,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37.</note> 
                     <hi>they were ſtoned, they were ſawed aſunder, they were tempted, they were ſlaine with the ſword, they wandred up and downe in Sheepe-skins, and Goat-skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented:</hi> And all this to teach us, that it is not the greatneſſe of Riches, nor the ſtatelineſſe of Pallaces, nor the favour of Princes, no, nor the reall and true-hearted affection of God himſelfe towards his Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, which will free them from ſuffering afflictions in this life.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.35. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Eſay</hi> 32.6.</note> Come hither then eſpecially all yee that <hi>flouriſh like a greene Bay-tree: Will you adde affliction to</hi> affliction? <hi>Will you make emptie the ſoule of the hungry, and cauſe the drinke of the thirſtie to faile?</hi> Will you looke upon the poore and needie with the eyes of ſcorne and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as though their caſes could never be your owne? And if there be a poſſibilitie, if the greene Tree may be withered, hewen downe, and caſt into the fire; why is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4863:9"/> there ſo much oppreſſion and extortion, ſo much uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſſe and complaining in our ſtreets? Surely, if there were not a day to come, it were much better to be an <hi>Indian Bird,</hi> and there to be ſed (as they thinke) upon charitie, then here to be a <hi>poore Chriſtian,</hi> and ſtarve for hunger, lye gaſping and panting in the ſtreetes for want of reliefe, and yet Art and Nature ſtretched our, to pleaſe other mens ſawcie and gluttonous appetites. Nay, this is not all: the Lord hath a quarrell, an irreconciliable quarrell, wherein he may call <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razin</hi> and <hi>Bethſuida</hi> to riſe up in judgement againſt thoſe who rob the Church of God, and <hi>grinde the faces of the poore,</hi> to make Bread <hi>dayly bread</hi> for brute Beaſts: As though that which is a part of the Chriſtians prayer, were to be made a portion for unreaſonable creatures: as though it were humanitie, to gather up the <hi>crummes</hi> which fall from the Manger; or charitie, to take the <hi>childrens bread,</hi> and give it to whelpes: Oh, why ſhould their mouthes be filled with ſuch abundance of mans nouriſhment, to encreaſe Gods wrath, and the preſent ſcarcitie? To come neerer my Text; why ſhould dumbe Dogges be ſooner heard, than the dolefull cries of poore priſoners, ingeminating their requeſts more for <hi>Bread, Bread,</hi> than libertie?</p>
                  <p n="7">7 There is a tradition worthy to be beleeved; That ſometimes a great Prelate of this Kingdome did thrice redeeme all the priſoners in <hi>London</hi> confin'd for Debt; but ſurely he died without iſſue: there's ſo much love of covetouſneſſe, or ſo much needleſſe feare of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted vaine-glorious, or ſo much vaine-glorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that poſteritie may ſee the viſible ſtructures and laſting monuments of a full (I cannot ſay a bountifull) hand, few or none inherit this kind of charitie: which, though it flouriſhed in many H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſes of Bondage, yet (I am ſure) it was never derived from the loines of this great <hi>Aegyptian;</hi> who beſides the common motives of humanitie and experience, going hand in hand (as you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4863:9"/> ſee) with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> had one Remembrancer more of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall note, to wit, his extraordinarie ſadneſſe; whereby the more ſenſible he muſt needes be of his owne impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, the leſſe reaſon he had to forget anothers, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Ioſephs,</hi> not onely his fellow priſoner, but (which is the next particular of his condition) a man of ſpeciall worth, an <hi>interpreter</hi> of his dreame, a remover of his ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>Yet did not the chiefe Butler, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8 Here we cannot ſtay, to behold the comelineſſe of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and the ingenuitie of his countenance, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by<note n="*" place="margin">Primo aspectu iudicans homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ingenuum &amp; honeſte na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. <hi>Philo. in l. de Ioſ.</hi> Gen. 39.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Pharaoh</hi> at the firſt ſight, as <hi>Philo</hi> tells us: a <hi>goodly perſon</hi> no queſtion hee was, and <hi>well-favoured</hi> (ſaith the Text) and that's ſomething to encreaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, where merit is the foundation, and might here have beene a motive of greater compaſſion.</p>
                  <p>Nor will we looke backe upon <hi>Ioſephs</hi> reputation in <hi>Potiphars</hi> houſe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.4.</note> where <hi>all things</hi> were left to be ordered and guided by his direction: in the managing whereof, it ſeemes he was not like that <hi>idle ſervant,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 25.25.</note> who hid his Maſters Talent; or like that <hi>unjuſt Steward,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.1.</note> who waſted his Maſters goods: it ſeemes he did not leſſen the yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Revenue, or mitigate the Fines, or any way under-value the price of his Maſters Lands, of purpoſe to make himſelfe a Gratuitie; a practice much feared, where the ſervant growes extraordinarie rich, &amp; the Maſter poore: No; by his wiſdome and providence all things ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded well, and proſpered in his Maſters behalfe;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.5.</note> 
                     <hi>the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Lord was upon all that he had in the houſe and in the field.</hi> The fame whereof (no queſtion) followed him to the Priſon, and there ſo pleaded his cauſe, that after a while he finds <hi>favour in the ſight of the Keeper,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. verſ.</hi> 21, 22.</note> 
                     <hi>all things are committed into his hand;</hi> and ſo he becomes charged with this great Officer, and his companion; who could not but perceive (though at a little hole, the hole of a Dungeon) the brightneſſe of his fidelitie, worthy of a larger, of a better imployment, and the rather regard that (his fidelitie) becauſe the want of it in themſelves
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4863:10"/> had begot the anger of a King, the puniſhment of a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the terrors of a guiltie Conſcience, the matter of a fearefull Dreame, the cauſe of this ſadneſſe; which in the chiefe Butler might have increaſed beyond expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had not <hi>Ioſeph</hi> beene an Interpreter, and thereby te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified that worth which now wee intend to diſcover: <hi>Yet did not the chiefe Butler, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9 Though the naturall man cannot diſcerne the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Grace, the beſt meanes of happineſſe; yet his loſſes by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> are not ſo great, but he is both ſenſible of his wants, and greedie to repaire them. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the corners of Nature have beene ſearched, to ſee if there were any voice of joy and gladneſſe in their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations: Nay, leaſt thoſe <hi>futura contingentia,</hi> contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, uncertainties to come, ſhould reſt in ſilence, even the Heathen people have made themſelves (<hi>Wiſe men</hi> ſo called) to fore-tell events; ſuch as amongſt the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> were knowne by the name of <hi>Chaldeans; Chaldeans</hi> not by Nation, but profeſſion; a name attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the moſt learned in that facultie: in <hi>Perſia,</hi> they were moſt properly called <hi>Magicians;</hi> in <hi>Greece, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers;</hi> amongſt the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> they were ſtiled <hi>Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, Scribes, Phariſees;</hi> and amongſt the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> they were tearmed <hi>Prieſts:</hi> even the Land of <hi>Aegypt</hi> became a Nurſerie for the Art of Divination, a blacke Art, farre beyond the light of fleſh and bloud; for in Nature wee finde onely three ſorts of cauſes, to regulate our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments concerning events. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſome cauſes doe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily and alwayes produce the ſame effects, and theſe effects (as the Eclipſes of the yeere) may be certainely fore-ſeene. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> ſome cauſes doe not alwayes, and neceſſarily, but commonly, and for the moſt part, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame effects; and theſe effects (as the ſeverall changes of the Weather) may be fore-ſeene too, but by way of conjecture onely. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> ſome cauſes are indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently diſpoſed <hi>ad oppoſita,</hi> to contrarie effects; and theſe effects (as for a man in perfect health, to goe or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4863:10"/> ſtand, to be ſick or die ſuch a day, at one time more than another) I ſay theſe effects cannot be fore-ſeene, or ſeene, but when they are preſent. And yet the learning of the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> will needes goe further, and as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>uſurpare futuro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um ut futura ſint notitiam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">22.95.1 <hi>C.</hi>
                     </note> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell events, without the conſideration of any cauſe: whereupon their intelligence ſeeming above Nature, and guided as it were by a divine ſpirit, their worth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came more admired, and their perſons promoted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.48.</note> Hereupon the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> being taken as one of that number, for ſhewing and interpreting the Kings Dreame, was preferred over all the Province of <hi>Babylon.</hi> In <hi>Rome,</hi> whileſt the State was governed by Senatours, we may clearely ſee their priviledges: there they had a Colledge of <hi>Augures,</hi> or <hi>Magicians,</hi> (whoſe walls I feare are not yet demoliſhed) their authoritie was ſo great, that whatſoever they deſigned, was ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Law: <hi>Qui non paruerit capitalis eſto,</hi> as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeakes in his ſecond Booked <hi>de Leg.</hi> Whoſoever will not obey, let him be held a capitall offender.<note n="*" place="margin">Ep. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Pliny</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Arius,</hi> calls other dignities <hi>propemodum paria,</hi> almoſt equall in reputation: Nay, being one of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber himſelfe, he pleads antiquitie for reſpect, and calls it <hi>priſcum Sacerdotium,</hi> an ancient Prieſthood,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> derived it ſeemes (as all Learning was) from theſe <hi>Aegyptians;</hi> which perhaps is the reaſon, why the ſame word in the originall being applyed to them, ſignifies both a <hi>Prieſt</hi> and a <hi>Prince, Chap.</hi> 41. <hi>v.</hi> 50. as though their authoritie were equall. No queſtion it was very<note n="*" place="margin">Augurum mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na tunc erat tum copia tum autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas.</note> great, as appeares afterward by <hi>Ioſephs</hi> promotion, who was alwayes held for one of that number, <hi>tantum religio potuit ſuadere malorum:</hi> So much was this prophane Art of Divination reſpected and practiſed amongſt the greateſt in the Kingdome, entertained ſooner than a better thing, and rewarded accordingly; rewarded did I ſay: yes ſurely; for the Prieſts ſhare was not Onions and Garlicke, but the third part of all this large and moſt fruitfull Land;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4863:11"/> treble the value of that, whereat the whole World ſeemes to murmure and exclaime in theſe dayes.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 In this Art, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſeemes to comply with the <hi>Magicians,</hi> by fore-telling things which afterward came to paſſe; but yet with much difference in the <hi>end,</hi> and <hi>meanes</hi> of his knowledge: for the knowledge of the <hi>Magicians,</hi> was by a wicked manner of Divination, whereof there are many kindes unworthy to be named; whoſe <hi>end,</hi> is vaine curioſitie; and the <hi>meanes,</hi> grand or groſſe Idolatry; either an expreſſe, or a tacite confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with the Devill: but <hi>Ioſephs</hi> knowledge was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall; whoſe <hi>end,</hi> is the manifeſtation of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and the <hi>meanes,</hi> a ſpeciall revelation from Heaven. Indeed, after his promotion, we read, that his ſervant ſpeakes of a <hi>Cup, wherein</hi> (hee ſaith) <hi>his Maſter doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 44.5.</note> but it ſeemes agreed on all ſides, that ſuch language was either according to that manner of Divination by the Cup, frequent among the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and ſo anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that opinion which they held of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> for a <hi>Magician;</hi> or to blinde the eyes of his brethren, from ſeeing his propheticall Spirit, before hee would reveale himſelfe: otherwiſe we cannot thinke, that hee who in the time of his diſtreſſe kept the Commandement, would in proſperitie renounce it, forſake the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and comply with <hi>Magicians,</hi> in the <hi>end</hi> and <hi>meanes</hi> of their knowledge; though they ſeeme to agree in the ſubſtance, by fore-telling things which afterward came to paſſe. And ſo much was apparant to the chiefe Butler, it came within the compaſſe of his apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for he heard an interpretation of his owne Dreame, and by ſeeing the predictions verified in himſelfe, hee never ſaw the like before. Nay, leaſt this intelligence ſhould be thought ſome impoſture, hee ſaw it ſeconded by another interpretation of the chiefe Bakers Dreame, wherein the truth of predictions found like ſucceſſe: Like ſucceſſe ſhall I ſay? Yes; for evidence, not for conſolation: for when they were both offenders, full
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4863:11"/> of diſtracted thoughts, animated with nothing elſe but feares and ſadneſſe; even then <hi>Joſephs</hi> interpretation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakes the chiefe Butlers Dreame, frees him from Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, reſtores his Office, ſaves his life, preſerves his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes: and where there is no future happineſſe of the ſoule thought on, what good turne could be more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, more ſeaſonable, more gratefull, eſpecially at that time, when the ſame ſpirit of interpretation which freed one, hanged another; the better to make him who eſcaped, remember both his deliverance and his friend?</p>
                  <p n="11">11 And yet for all this, <hi>Joſephs</hi> worth did moſt of all appeare, by confeſſing the meanes and Author of his knowledge: which he inſinuates by a queſtion;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 40.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Doe not interpretations belong to God?</hi> Which words, though they would not ſinke into the head of this <hi>Aegyptian</hi> at that time (being a priſoner,) yet afterwards (being a Courtier) they might well perſwade a further inquirie; if not for the goodneſſe, yet for the noveltie of ſuch direction: But the goodneſſe (had it beene perceived, as who would not have tryed whether this Spirit came downe from Heaven, or no?) was a Cup of greater bleſſing, than the River <hi>Nilus</hi> overflowing the whole Land of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> ſuch (as for ought hee knew to the contrarie) might have <hi>taught the Senatours wiſedome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.22.</note> reformed the Superſtition of that Age, rectified the judgement of all: ſo faire an opportunitie did <hi>Ioſeph</hi> give the chiefe Butler, to lay a foundation of greater honour, of ſpeciall advantage for himſelfe, had hee but given this Cup of rare Divination into <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hand. But worth of the higheſt nature, findes little reſpect where it is not apprehended; and being apprehended, obtaines not much more, unleſſe it be found beneficiall and profitable to mens preſent occaſions: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, either <hi>Ioſephs</hi> worth in this kinde was not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood at all; and then he was very unhappie, (as many are upon like occaſions) in applying his worth to that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4863:12"/> man who underſtands it not: or this <hi>Aegyptian</hi> hath ſome reaſons to the contrarie, of greater importance; whereat wee may gueſſe, in the diſcoverie of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 In the meane time, we may returne to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Worke: and whileſt we behold it finiſhed, the interpretation made, the prediction verified, and the happineſſe of it in poſſeſſion; let us conſider, that as this is ſufficient for the ends of a naturall man, ſo it may be for his remembrance too; that remembrance, which includes a continuall thankes and acknowledgement; that thankes, which is ſealed with a due requitall, when occaſion ſerves; even a perfect thankfulneſſe, as well in effect, as in ſhew and deſire: eſpecially the worth of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and fore-telling events; being an act in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſo highly eſteemed by the faſhion and ſuperſtition of that countrey, and here in particular ſo full of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, by the teſtimonie of his owne experience; nay, ſo greedily embraced, by the conſent and neceſſitie of all his occaſions: and the rather, becauſe the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> of all others, are famous for workes of thankefulneſſe, not onely towards their gods and men, but even to brute beaſts alſo, as <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> obſerves: Nay, they ſeeme in a manner to have taught the brute beaſts themſelves this qualitie: for beſides the thankefulneſſe of the Dog, (very common, and remarkable) their Hieroglyphicke for a gratefull minde,<note place="margin">Pieri. Val. l. <hi>17.</hi> pag. <hi>158.</hi>
                     </note> is the <hi>Storke;</hi> which (as Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans tell us) provides a Neſt, and prepares nouriſhment for the old one, after the ſame manner, and in the ſame place wherein ſhe was brought up her ſelfe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me thinkes an <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> of all others, ſhould not ſo much incurre the cenſure of his owne countrey, ſo much prejudice the reputation of his owne judgement, ſo much violate the preſervation of common honeſty, as not to pay this morall debt, of a thankfull remembrance.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <note place="margin">Plut. in vita Alex.</note>13 Wee reade, that the laſt gaſpe of great King <hi>Darius</hi> (being wounded by ſome of his ſervants, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4863:12"/> forſaken by them all) breathed thankfulneſſe to <hi>Poliſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> a <hi>Macedonian,</hi> for giving him a cup of cold water to drinke. And it is this vertue, which makes theſe ancient Women of <hi>Rome</hi> yet alive, freſh in remembrance;<note place="margin">Sabell. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> exemp.</note> who (becauſe <hi>Junius Brutus</hi> had revenged the raviſhment of <hi>Lucretia</hi>) they all (in a thankefull acknowledgement of that pious fact) mourned for his death a whole yeere together. But examples have their time, Nature endures for ever; and her Law (we know) gives honour to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as cauſes of our being: Whereupon (according to that of <hi>Aquinas;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aq.</hi> 22.106.3. <hi>C.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Benefactor in quantum hujuſmodi eſt cauſa beneficiati;</hi> A Benefactor in ſome ſort is the cauſe of him who receives the benefit) wee may well inferre, that the giver may challenge of the receiver a dutie of thankfulneſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Benefactori quidem in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum huiuſmodi debetur honor &amp; reverentia, eo quod habet ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem principii. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </note> honour, and reverence, the proper duties of all effects to their cauſe. But it may be the <hi>Graces</hi> ſpeake more familiar language: they (we ſee) are pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>complexis dextris,</hi> joyning hand in hand, <hi>ut redditio beneficii notetur,</hi> to expreſſe their inviolable connexion, and the neceſſitie of thankefulneſſe in all humane ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. So that he hath little reaſon to breake this ſacred confederation, who expects no other happineſſe but by the Law of Nature.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 And if there be ſo much to perſwade a naturall man, then ſurely the Chriſtian muſt not come behinde: And yet what needes any other invitation? Nature like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is the Chriſtians familiar friend, and her Law muſt be his direction. Sure I am, there needs no other exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but that of King <hi>David,</hi> in the ſecond of <hi>Samuel, ch.</hi> 9. who asked, if there were <hi>any left of Sauls houſe, to whom hee might ſhew kindneſſe?</hi> It ſeemes that reſolution of <hi>Tully</hi> was his Motto,<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de ſinib. bon &amp; mal.</note> 
                     <hi>Volo eſſe &amp; haberi gratus,</hi> I will be thankefull, and ſo accounted: for marke the event; upon this inquiry, <hi>Siba</hi> the ſervant of <hi>Ionathan</hi> is brought in, and he brings in <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Jonathan:</hi> And ſhould not <hi>David</hi> have reſpected <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> the ſole remainder of <hi>Sauls</hi> houſe? And which is more, the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4863:13"/> ſonne of <hi>Ionathan: Ionathan,</hi> who loved him as his owne ſoule; who incurr'd his fathers high diſpleaſure, and much endangered his owne life for his ſake; by whoſe faithfull advice and direction, <hi>David</hi> was alwaies taught how to behave himſelfe in Court, and to avoid the Kings furie: I ſay, ſhould not <hi>David</hi> have loved <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> the ſoule of <hi>Jonathan</hi> might by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant have cryed to Heaven for vengeance. But <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth</hi> was regarded; and all that belonged to <hi>Saul</hi> and his houſehold, was conferr'd upon him. The bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this favour reflects upon <hi>Ziba</hi> too; for he is made Steward (as it were) to <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> to husband and manage his lands: whereby he alſo, and his ſonnes and his ſervants might bleſſe King <hi>David,</hi> the remembrance of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> and all enjoy the fruits of this moſt gratefull and princely minde.</p>
                  <p n="15">15 And thus, if thankfulneſſe, by a <hi>Kings example,</hi> be written in Capitall Letters; whoſe proud, or careleſſe, or greedie and covetous eye will paſſe by, and not regard it? If he make thankfulneſſe, like <hi>precious Ointment,</hi> run downe to the skirts of his clothing; who will not touch the <hi>hemme</hi> of that <hi>garment,</hi> eſpecially to cure the <hi>bloudie iſſue</hi> of malice, where the debt is of a contrary nature, a debt of love and kindneſſe? In a word, if the King vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe ſo much favour to <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> who called himſelfe <hi>a dead Dog;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.8.</note> then ſurely they are worſe than dead Dogs, who upon like occaſions will not (as <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> did) bow unto the <hi>King;</hi> much more, and in the firſt place, to the King of Kings, the Lord of Hoſts, the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from whom alone we receive our being, life, and motion, preſervation from dangers, and aſſiſtance in theſe holy exerciſes:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.8. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 116.15.</note> 
                     <hi>O that men would</hi> therefore <hi>praiſe the Lord for his goodneſse, and offer unto him a ſacrifice of thanksgiving;</hi> never receiving any benefit, never ſpeaking of his works, never thinking of his Name, without making that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael from everlaſting to everlaſting, and let all the people ſay, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4863:13"/>16 And for a better illuſtration of this thankfulneſſe to God, ſince he hath commanded us to honour our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, let it be the pietie and Religion of our Countrey, the height of gratitude, to <hi>give unto Caeſar that which is Caeſars;</hi> and in like proportion, to obſerve all thoſe who in publike or private affaires deſerve well at our hands, and appeare to be men of worth and authority. In which reſpect (were it in another place) I ſhould a little plead the caſe of an <hi>Interpreter</hi> (as moſt proper to my Text:) but being here, I will onely preſent ſome few materials of juſt exception, to be adviſed upon and drawne up into better forme by more learned Counſell.</p>
                  <p n="17">17 'Tis true, wee are bound not by Superſtition, but Religion, the Religion of our Countrey, to reſpect <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters,</hi> not of Dreames, but Lawes; not mans Lawes, but Gods; threatning more certaine, more fearefull events: We have likewiſe the manner of this reſpect ſet downe in 1 <hi>Corinth. chap.</hi> 4. to eſteeme them <hi>as Miniſters of God, and ſtewards</hi> of divine Myſteries: beſides we clearely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their interpretations to proceed from God; and the fruits thereof dayly ſpringing up within the centre of our owne hearts, taking away the Curſe of an infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Dungeon, and all ſadneſſe from our eyes; each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular circumſtance in the whole courſe of our lives crying aloud, and calling upon us, to regard them according to the dignitie of their calling, the excellencie of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. But (alas) how doth this appeare, when men doe not reſpect the <hi>perſon of the Prieſt?</hi> whereof the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy</hi> complaines, and makes it one;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.16.</note> and another of his lamentations, That hee was <hi>a deriſion to the people,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.14.63.</note> 
                     <hi>their muſicke, their ſong all the day long.</hi> Nay, the Worlds ſober practice thinks, that ſacred calling makes a man as it were an underling, leſſens the degree and reputation of his birth; as though it were no addition of honour, to be <hi>Gods</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</note> 
                     <hi>Embaſſadour, a</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Meſſenger of the Churches, the glory of Chriſt:</hi> no honourable imployment, but an Office of ſervitude, a ſtaine and blemiſh to his qualitie; whence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4863:14"/> perhaps it is, that men ſeldome conſecrate their firſt-borne unto the Lord. No: this ſacred Office (the Office of a Miniſter) is thought too meane (forſooth) for the greatneſſe of an elder brother; and yet their Patrimony, their Tithes, moſt convenient for his Lay Inheritance, coveted more, and upon worſe tearmes, than <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard; ſometimes the whole body of maintenance divided, ſometimes all in a manner taken away; nothing reſerved for the Church, but the gall (as it were) the worſt for uſe, and fitteſt for a bitter jeſt. Nay, that which is reſerved (ſome thinke) may well be taken away; and that the Miniſters of the Goſpel can challenge nothing of right, but muſt be fed (not much unlike children) from hand to mouth, upon almes, and a voluntarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution: and therefore men care not to <hi>rob God,</hi> as hee himſelfe complaines in the third of <hi>Malachy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8.</note> by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing <hi>Tithes and Offerings;</hi> ſtriving by contracts, by cuſtomes, the corruption of times, plaine uſurpations, and by devices fetched from Hell, to make the Clergy poore and contemptible: as though it were their crowne of pride and rejoycing, the fitteſt proportion anſwerable to each mans worth, to ſee themſelves clothed in <hi>Biſſe</hi> the footman in Velvet, the Prophet in Sackcloth; he a poore man, ready to <hi>give his</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
                     <hi>hand to Aegyptians, to be ſatisfied with bread;</hi> themſelves, like the rich glutton, faring <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly every day.</hi> Is this the way to honour the dignitie of that ſacred calling? or not rather, the next way to make the <hi>worſt of the people Prieſts of the high places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor is their proceeding more favourable than the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: for ſome we ſee quite forgotren, lie obſcure, and buried (as it were) in the midſt of their owne moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Works; whileſt others, acquainted only with a few beggerly rudiments, the impudence of a bawling lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or a temporizing judgement, are ſet on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe: theſe have much adoe to be <hi>Doore keepers</hi> in the houſe of the Lord; but theſe, riding upon flying Horſes, whoſe wings are of Silver, and their feathers of Gold,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4863:14"/> mount up quickly to the pinacles of the Temple: theſe, like <hi>Joſeph,</hi> lye impriſoned in a vale of miſerie, and a val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of teares, in a deepe Dungeon of a round figure, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in none can ſtand upright, none remaine without a ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded poſture, a dejected countenance, a diſcontented mind, finding few friends to remember them;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Am</hi> 6.4.</note> but theſe <hi>lye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Beds of Ivorie, ſtretch themſelves upon their Couches,</hi> like Pictures drawne out at length, and like <hi>Simon Magus</hi> have a familiar whereſoever they goe, to carry them up to the top of the Mountaine; where being tempted and overcome with a large and vain-glorious Proſpect, they ride poſting up and downe, (and for more haſt, changing at every ſtage) to take poſſeſſion of that worldly pompe for which they have fallen downe and worſhipped the unrighteous <hi>Mammon,</hi> the <hi>Prince of darkeneſse:</hi> And yet ſuch proceedings, the judgement of this Age eſteemes the beſt interpretations of worth, and the ſtrongeſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of wiſdome and providence.</p>
                  <p n="18">18 But though ſome knock, and no man openeth, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be that of the Poet, <hi>ſtabis Homere foras,</hi> an expreſſe deniall of entrance, or a pretended excuſe; yet others perhaps are thought to finde a little favour, and like the <hi>Levite</hi> in the 17. of <hi>Iudges,</hi> are entertained in privat hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: but it is much feared, more for faſhion ſake, than Religion; more to hold a correſpondencie with State, than devotion: otherwiſe they would not be kept at ſuch an awfull diſtance as many times they are, but uſed in a more familiar manner;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.32.</note> thought worthy (no <hi>abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi>) to ſit at their Tables, to whom they carve the Bread of Life,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 8.31.</note> and received into the Chariot (as <hi>Philip</hi> was by the Eunuch) to be his guide and interpreter; much leſſe ſhould their worth, at the mercenarie pleaſure of a corrupt follower, groaning under the burthens of pride and covetouſneſſe, ſtand or fall in the Maſters opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Is this the way to underdand the worth of <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters?</hi> But marke the concluſion: either their greateſt favour in the end, is an opportunitie of giving a Bribe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4863:15"/> ſooner than another man; or the hire of the labourer, the portion of <hi>Levi;</hi> the long expectation of his ſervice, even thoſe ſacred and maſculine preferments of the Church, are by a plauſible kind of Sacriledge enforc'd to a tranſmutation of Sex: Nay (which is much feared, as moſt damnable) they are ſometime made like the Signet and Bracelets of <hi>Thamar,</hi> the reward of a Harlot: In which caſe it may well be ſaid, this <hi>Marriage</hi> is not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, nor that <hi>Bed</hi> undefiled: and yet (I feare) there are too many, who water ſuch <hi>Couches</hi> with their teares; whereby <hi>Beneficium in maleficium,</hi> they obtaine a Curſe, for a Bleſſing; in ſtead of a reward, they are made a ſcorne, a by-word, a laughing-ſtock to the whole world. Is this the way to requite the paines, and gratifie the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Gods <hi>Embaſſadours?</hi> Have wee ſo learned Chriſt, who ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16. <hi>He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me; and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me?</hi> Surely, if interpretations belong to God as the author, they belong to man as the object: and then the Meſſenger betwixt God and man deſerves a better requitall, unleſſe we deſire to make our ſelves objects of his furie &amp; everlaſting diſpleaſure, who hates the works of unthankefulneſſe both towards God and man. Shall Superſtition make more of her Prieſts, than Religion of ours? then ſurely it is much better to be the chiefe But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſervant, than his <hi>Interpreter: Joſeph</hi> was both for a while; and (which is the laſt particular of his condition) <hi>a petitioner</hi> too: <hi>Yet did not the chiefe Butler remember Joſeph, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For this likewiſe I am prepared: But the particulars of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> petition, ſet downe in the 14. and 15. Verſes of this Chapter, ſeeme reaſons of denyall, in the chiefe But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers condition, ſo that we cannot well ſpeake of the one without the other; and both together, will treſpaſſe too much upon your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, being ſufficient for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oportunitie,</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4863:15"/>
                  <p>THE AEGYPTIAN COVRTIER.</p>
                  <p>THE SECOND SERMON.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>HORA. Serm. Li. 1. Sat. 4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <l>Qui non defendit alio culpante —</l>
                     <l>— Hic niger eſt hunc tu Romane caveto.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>EZEK. 29. VER. 6.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And all the inhabitants of Aegypt ſhall know, that I am the Lord, becauſe they have beene a ſtaffe of Reed to the houſe of Iſrael.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed for HENRY SEILE. 1635.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4863:16"/>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4863:16"/>
                  <head>THE AEGYPTIAN COVRTIER. <hi>The ſecond Sermon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>GEN. 40. VER. 23.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Yet did not the chiefe Butler remember <hi>IOSEPH,</hi> but forgot him.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p n="1">1<seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the bond of all ſocietie (eſpecially that dayly intercourſe amongſt men) is beſt preſerved by a mutuall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of each others condition: So all relations and cenſures muſt paſſe by the ſame acquaintance, as the only meanes to animate and regulate their proceedings. In which reſpect, having met with two perſons of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent qualitie, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and the <hi>chiefe Butler,</hi> wee have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore made their ſeverall conditions the two generall parts of this Text; that ſo by diſcovering the motives of remembrance in the <hi>one,</hi> and by gueſſing at the reaſons of forge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fulneſſe in the <hi>other,</hi> the matter it ſelfe might be more worthy of attention, and the cenſure more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie upon him who deſerves it.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4863:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4863:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4863:18"/>
                  <p>In <hi>Ioſephs</hi> condition were obſerved three particulars: the <hi>firſt,</hi> of a <hi>priſoner;</hi> the <hi>ſecond,</hi> of an <hi>Interpreter;</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> and laſt, of a <hi>petitioner:</hi> the two former have beene delivered at large in this place; the other ſtayed behind, for a better tryall of the chiefe Butler, and his condition. Now all the remainder is readie to be preſented: but firſt, the next in order proves like it ſelfe, a <hi>Petitioner,</hi> for your favour and patience, to heare an end of the whole buſineſſe.</p>
                  <p>And yet before wee proceed any further, it muſt not be thought any vaine repetition, to ſumme up all that hath beene ſpoken, by reducing it to a word or two.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 2 Firſt then, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was a <hi>priſoner,</hi> ſo the chiefe Butlers humanitie, and experience of the ſame miſerie, might well make him remember his fellow priſoner; eſpecially conſidering his owne extraordinarie ſadneſſe, occaſioned by a Dreame at the ſame time, which ſurely afterwards he could never forget.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And then, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was an <hi>Interpreter,</hi> the interpreter of a Dreame; ſo the chiefe Butler might be taught by his mothers wit, by the faſhion and ſuperſtition of his countrey, to remember him as a man of great worth, worth of the higheſt nature, by the common voice of all <hi>Aegypt;</hi> much more might he requite this Interpreter, for removing the ſadneſſe of his Dreame, and that chiefely at ſuch a time, when the ſame ſpirit of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which recalled one to the pleaſures of life, delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red another to the terrors of death; the better (as might be then well enlarged by your owne private meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) to make him who was reſtored to his Office, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eate Bread, nor drinke Wine; neither lye downe to ſleepe, nor riſe up to play; never ſee a cluſter of Grapes, or a basket of bak'd meates; or Fowles upon the Kings Table, or Birds flying in the Aire; never bow the knee to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or give the Cup into his hand, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring both the manner of his deliverance, and the condition of his friend; not onely a <hi>priſoner,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4863:18"/> to be relieved; not onely an <hi>interpreter</hi> of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ranke, and therefore highly to be rewarded: but (which is the laſt particular of his condition, and comes now to be handled) a <hi>petitioner</hi> too: <hi>Yet did not the chiefe Butler remember Ioſeph, but forgot him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 Hitherto then you have ſeene <hi>Ioſephs miſerie,</hi> and you have heard his <hi>worth,</hi> whereby you muſt needes thinke him the fitteſt man to be an humble ſuiter: for by the one (his miſerie) he cannot want matter; and by the other (his worth) he is beſt able to contrive the forme of a ſad and diſcreet petition: and yet when free retired meditations of a ſublime and Angelicall nature are curb'd and cruſh'd by the clowniſh and ſawcie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion of theſe diſtracting thoughts, thoughts of want and extremitie; when this extremitie may be expoſed to the griefe and trouble of friends, to the hiſſing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation of enemies, to the ſhame and ſleighting of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, to the cenſures and Table-talke of ſtrangers, to the ſcorne, or pitie, or wonder, or laughter of all; when all this may be aggravated by the qualitie of the perſon, the condition of his former eſtate, the greatneſſe of his ſpirit, the tenderneſſe of his conſcience, the uncertaintie of his hopes, the inconſtancie of favour, the hardneſſe and corruption of the times: But when this aggravation may be enlarged (as here it fell out) by reflecting upon the cauſe, falſe accuſations cunningly diſguiſed, imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of faithleſneſſe and diſhoneſtie, inrolling the loſſe of a good name; theſe, oh theſe preſented to authority, countenanced by impudence, proſecuted by wilfulneſſe, entertained by credulitie, reſolved by partialitie, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the indignation of great perſons, to the height of malice, to the depth of impriſonment, to the <hi>bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſoule,</hi> to the fulneſſe of oppreſſion, <hi>oppreſſion which makes a wiſe man mad, Eccl.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7. What heart (though never ſo well tempered for the greateſt deſignes in Church or State) can breath out any voice but that of the Pſalmiſt: <hi>Oh that I had the wings of a Dove,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.6.</note> 
                     <hi>that I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4863:19"/> might flie away, and be at reſt;</hi> or ſpend any time, but in ſighes and ſobs; petitions not to be expreſſed, unleſſe they be very ſhort, and ſo was this (thereby fitteſt for a Courtiers liking) as you may reade it in the 14. and 15. Verſes of this Chapter: There I am ſure it was delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; for it was ſpoken, not written; and that not by another, but himſelfe: <hi>Thinke on me</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>when it ſhall be well with thee, and ſhew kindneſse J pray thee unto me, and make mention of me unto Pharaoh, and bring me out of this houſe, for I was ſtolne out of the Land of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes; and here alſo have J done nothing why they ſhould put me into the dungeon.</hi> Here's the Petition: Had <hi>Ioſeph</hi> truſted either his paper or his friend to preſent it, the one might have beene read at leiſure, the other might have wearied his expectation, or perhaps durſt not have ſpoken without a licence from <hi>Potiphar:</hi> and ſo in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, neither of them prove better than both together (if I may ſo ſay) a <hi>Paper-friend,</hi> capable of impreſſion on both ſides: but the Petition was delivered, whereof both the matter ſeemes very reaſonable, and each cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance beyond exception. For firſt you ſee, without any preface of<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob</hi> 32.21.</note> 
                     <hi>flattering Titles,</hi> the givers folly, the receivers pride; whereof <hi>Joſeph</hi> it ſeemes will not be taxed for the one himſelfe, nor be thought to ſuſpect the other in this <hi>Aegyptian.</hi> The chiefe thing deſired, is full of modeſtie, <hi>onely to be brought out of that houſe,</hi> eſpecially that place of a Dungeon: which (as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) having but one paſſage into it, and that both a window for light, and a doore for entrance, makes the requeſt not much unlike that of <hi>Diogenes</hi> to Great <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plut in vit. Alex.</note> That the Sunne might not be kept from him; onely to be freed from that darke circumference, whoſe noyſome vapours might well infect the places adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and make <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> as well a <hi>keeper</hi> as a <hi>priſoner,</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be brought out of ſuch a houſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The reaſons are very forcible: the <hi>one,</hi> that he was no baniſhed man from his owne countrey, no runnagate,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4863:19"/> no malefactor, but hee was <hi>ſtolne out of the Land of the Hebrewes:</hi> the <hi>other,</hi> that hee had done no offence ſince his comming into <hi>Aegypt, nothing worthy of the Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 The meanes likewiſe are very commendable: the <hi>one ſubordinate,</hi> the chiefe Butlers kindneſſe; the <hi>other principall,</hi> the Kings notice: his kindneſſe, to procure a diſcharge; the Kings notice, to grant it: his kindneſſe (in caſe of oppoſition) for true information; the Kings notice, for ſpeedie juſtice; both<note n="*" place="margin">Talium rerum uſus ſpem &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duciam divini auxilii nec tollit, nec minuit. <hi>Pere. de inter. ſomniorum a Ioſeph in carcere.</hi>
                     </note> lawfull in themſelves, honourable for a Kingdome, and neceſſarie for his triall; who deſires by faire and indifferent meanes to teſtifie his innocence, and redeeme his libertie.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 And now the matter being thus reaſonable, makes the ſucceſſe very probable: had it beene a matter of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had denyed himſelfe, by asking it; but all things of like nature are eaſily granted, where there is nothing hard to be beleeved; and here's nothing to be ſuſpected, nothing can be but the <hi>reaſons,</hi> whereof the <hi>one</hi> wants an accuſer; in which caſe, it were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to beleeve that hee was ſtolne out of the Land of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> than goe thither to trie it: the <hi>other</hi> (his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence) hath no accuſation but a womans malice; a partie, no ſufficient proofe; a Wife indeed, whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint might well make her Husband diſtaſte and caſhiere his ſervant, not ſeverely puniſh him, without a legall witneſſe. Howſoever, as it is well obſerved by S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome, Ioſeph</hi> deſcends not to any particulars in<note n="*" place="margin">Nihil addens de iniquitate fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum, nihil de nequitia herae ſuae cum utram<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> hic poſſit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firinger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Muſc.</hi>
                     </note> this, or his other reaſon, as that he was ſtolne and ſold by his owne brethren; and that though hee was farre-fetch'd, yet hee was not dearely bought, as hee might have been, had hee fed the laſcivious eye of his Maſters Wife, and been partaker in her adulterie; that hee was carefull to reſiſt and prevent her dayly ſollicitations; that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greedie of an opportunitie, found one, layes hold upon him, but all in vaine, <hi>pro I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e nubem,</hi> ſhe could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine nothing but his Garment: that this Relique ſhee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4863:20"/> kept in a Cloyſter (ſafe enough, no queſtion) as a matter of wonder for others, of advantage for her ſelfe: and that ſo it fell out; for by a ſpeedie tranſmutation of luſt into malice, as though ſhe had formerly been taught the practice of his brethren, who ſtript him of his <hi>party-coloured Coat,</hi> to accuſe the wilde beaſts, to delude the old man their father, and to free themſelves from ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſo ſhee, in like manner, had made the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">Ipſa igitur quod celare debuerat prodebat ut com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito crimine lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret innocentem. <hi>Amb. in li. 5. de Ioſ.</hi>
                     </note> Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a witneſſe to accuſe his honeſtie, and to magnifie her owne; and ſo that which was left behinde as a pledge, to teſtifie his innocence, ſhee makes a cloake to cover her owne<note n="*" place="margin">Ill im vere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utam dixerim etiam aliena ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimenta ſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, qua omnia amiſerat vela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina caſtitatis. <hi>Amb. ibid.</hi>
                     </note> nakedneſſe, and a hood to blinde her Husbands eyes. And that beſides all this, if the truth hereof, or the generalitie of his good behaviour in times paſt will not be juſtified by his fellow ſervants, <hi>in promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu cauſa eſt,</hi> the reaſon is plaine; his falſe accuſer, was the <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> of the houſe; and his Iudge, the <hi>Maſter</hi> of it: And <hi>if a Ruler hearken unto lyes,</hi> (much more, if he practice them himſelfe) <hi>all his ſervants are wicked, Prov.</hi> 29. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. I ſay, all theſe particulars ſleepe in ſilence; and<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc unum eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, non ut illos condemnet, ſed ut proſe ſolo dicat. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
                     </note> hee ſeemes onely to ſtudie this one thing (which indeed ſhould be every mans car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) how he may ſpeake for himſelfe without condemning, without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing others: though he might have declared the whole circumſtance, as matter of inſtruction, to informe the King, to ſatisfie gainſayers, and to anſwer all objections; yet (it ſeemes) he thinkes it better (as indeed it is) both in point of wiſdome and Religion, to conceale the faults of others (at leaſt men of qualitie) as much as may be; and (though all griefe is leſſened, in being communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) ſeldome or never to reveale any particular paſſages of injurie before private men (eſpecially ſuch as can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adviſe nor compoſe the difference) but rather to referre them to ſome publike and judiciall examination; for thus (no queſtion) the <hi>Truth it ſelfe</hi> will be freeſt from ſuffering prejudice, the <hi>Tale bearer</hi> looſe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and pine away, the <hi>Defendant</hi> furtheſt from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4863:20"/> advantage, from preventing the puniſhment of his offence, and the <hi>Plaintife</hi> leaſt of all ſuſpected for any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſſe or partialitie in his owne cauſe.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 But I haſten: and (becauſe a good matter may be ſpoiled in the carriage) let the Petition be denied, if the ſucceſſe in any could be more probable than this, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the time wherein it was delivered; for it was made to the chiefe Butler, in the time of his ſad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, nay, in the Winter of his feares, in the Spring of his hopes; a time wherein men are apt to promiſe moſt, and moſt eaſie to be entreated.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Nor is it leſſe remarkable, that this Petition was made to him alone: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> addreſt himſelfe wholly to the chiefe Butler, without imploring the aſſiſtance of other friends, as being confident in his power and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: a paſſage (if I miſtake not) anſwerable in ſome ſort to the pride and expectation of many great ones in theſe dayes; who in the promotion of Suites, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of others, will be all, or nothing: like Lovers, like Kings, they admit no partners, no fellow-labourers: nay, like God himſelfe (who ſurely never commanded any ſuch reſemblance) they would be thought to make other men their creatures, and are highly pleaſed to have them called ſo; ſuch ambition and vaine-glory, ſuch private ends, ſuch hopes of entire reſpect, and blinde obſervance, (the deſignes of worldly wiſedome) lye hidden, and (as it were) enterlined betwixt the proteſtation and the performance of reall favours: ſo that hee who (for the diſpatch of his buſineſſe) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes more friends than one, (unleſſe they be ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate) takes the onely way to loſe them all, and his Cauſe to boot.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 Beſides, the Petition is made but once: as though hee had beene taught that in <hi>Ovid, Et pudet, &amp; metuo ſemperque eademque precari;</hi> to feare, and be aſhamed to entreat the ſame things oft; and this muſt be held a point of diſcretion too: for though in reſpect of God,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4863:21"/> whoſe infinite wiſedome is alwayes at leiſure, Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> commands us, <hi>pete, quaere, inſta,</hi> to be <hi>inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> to <hi>pray continually,</hi> yet in reſpect of men, whoſe underſtandings are bounded and limited, eſpecially ſuch whoſe high places are attended with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of great imployments, Petitions may be unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, frequent ſolicitations very unwelcome, many times beget neglect, nay, a cauſe of denyall, and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly too, unleſſe it be in caſes of extreme miſerie, or where the Iudge proves unjuſt; for then neceſſitie hath no law,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.10.</note> and importunitie (which was the poore Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes friend) may well be excuſed, if it ſpeake the Poets language, <hi>Da veniam vitio (mitis amice) meo;</hi> confeſſe the fault, and entreat a pardon.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 But here, though <hi>Joſephs</hi> affliction was very much, yet he might thinke, that ſince <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were the firſt (as <hi>Herodotus</hi> reports) who brought Altars and Images and Temples into the World, they will not be ſo unnaturall, ſo contrarie to themſelves and their owne invention, as to forget the Prieſt, eſpecially ſuch a Prieſt as brings downe from Heaven the image of the moſt High, and is himſelfe an Angell of Light, the light of this truth:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Doe not interpretations belong to God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11 Againe, he might hope, that ſince <hi>Aegyptians</hi> hold themſelves to be all Gentlemen (as Stories record) they will accordingly ſhew themſelves <hi>gentle, and eaſie to be entreated,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
                     <hi>full of mercie and good workes,</hi> the foundation of true Gentilitie; much more being thereunto invited by the wants, deſerts, and powerfull words of a divine Apoſtle, a rare Interpreter.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 Beſides, this was an opinion generally received throughout all <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and afterwards of all others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came moſt remarkable to poſteritie; <q rend="margQuotes">That the next way to root out wickedneſſe, was to puniſh the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, to ſupport the innocent, and to helpe all thoſe who were reduced to any great extremitie.</q> And therefore, ſince <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were obſerved to carry about
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4863:21"/> them the figures and repreſentations of brute Beaſts, Dogs, Crocodiles, and the like, ſhewing them a farre off as their preſerving gods; <hi>Ioſeph</hi> might well thinke the chiefe Butler would carry about him a leſſer burthen, a Iewell, the remembrance of a friend, a diſtreſſed friend, and make mention of him to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as a Meſſenger from Heaven, a reſtorer of his life and fortunes, a helper in the time of need.</p>
                  <p n="13">13 Howſoever, if theſe opinions were not begot or ripe enough in that Age; yet it might well be thought, the nobleneſſe of a great man need not be urged, where the Petition is not for preferment, but maintenance; maintenance in a good cauſe, and that ſo miſerable, ſo plaine a caſe. And yet how plaine a caſe ſoever it be, me thinkes the chiefe Butler heares and ſees, and ſayes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; nothing for the preſent, nothing for the future; I am ſure, nothing to the purpoſe: ſmall comfort for a miſerable man of ſpeciall worth, making ſuch a <hi>modeſt,</hi> and <hi>reaſonable</hi> and <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> Petition; whoſe deſerts were the more, and more to be regarded, by how much his affliction was ſo great, and his requeſt ſo ſmall.</p>
                  <p>Surely, I ſhould have taken ſilence for a part of his condition; but that at firſt it cannot be diſcerned, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was the ſtatelineſſe of his carriage, or that wiſe kind of denyall by delayes, or diſcretion, which made him rather imboſome the Petition than anſwere it. And yet ſtatelineſſe was not ſutable to that place, the place of a Dungeon; and (I am ſure) a denyall were of it ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, but by delayes, a torture; onely diſcretion may be pretended, and that onely for a while, till <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation ſucceed, and a faire opportunitie ſerve to move the King; whereof the chiefe Butler had many, very many, by reaſon of his condition, as will now appeare: <hi>Yet did not the chiefe Butler, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">14 I Am at laſt come to the condition of the chiefe Butler; which if I could demonſtrate, I ſhould be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4863:22"/> very briefe: but being onely to gueſſe at it, as ſhort as may be, ſuch as we have <hi>heard and ſeene,</hi> and ſuch as our fathers have told us: and therefore his condition ſhall be wrapt up onely in this one particular; he was a great Officer in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, reſtored to his Office, and therefore unlikely to remember <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> a <hi>Priſoner,</hi> an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter,</hi> a <hi>Petitioner:</hi> The probabilitie of this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence (for it is no more) will a little reſemble naturall wiſedome; whereby, as hee who ſtands, will <hi>take heed leſt he fall;</hi> ſo hee who was fallen, and ſtands againe, muſt needes more ſenſibly apprehend a poſſibilitie of change, and thereby more carefully endeavour a prevention of relapſe: For whereas this great Officer had offended <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and was therefore caſt from his Office, yet we finde him reſtored againe; by what meanes, the Text is ſilent. It could not be a diſcoverie of his innocence; 'tis plaine he had <hi>offended:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1.</note> And ſurely this offence was not as the <hi>Iewes</hi> affirme, becauſe a little Fly was fallen into the Cup; and yet ſo reported by them (ſaith <hi>Peter Martyr</hi>) to ſhew us, that great men for the moſt part are very prone to be angry, and ſeverely to puniſh too for ſmall offences (true <hi>Aegyptians</hi> it ſeemes) as though to be <hi>ſlow to wrath,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.19.</note> were no divine command, no wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome worth their having: for if it were ſuch a triviall offence, as the falling of a Fly into the Cup; then (me thinkes) a little time, eſpecially the time of a feaſt, much more the feaſt of a King to his ſervants, and that upon his birth-day, might eaſily have wrought out his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; ſuch a feaſt being uſually a time of ſpeciall grace and princely compaſſion, the fitteſt time to reſtore a chiefe Butler to his place againe, and to remit ſmall offences, without making any meanes at all. But ſo the chiefe Baker (who was hanged) might have beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed too; his fault being onely (as the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Fable goes) becauſe a little ſtone was found in the Bread: ſo ſmall a cauſe makes their caſes both alike; offences of careleſneſſe: they could not be of trecherie; for then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4863:22"/> common policie would never have reſtored either of them to ſuch places of dayly and neceſſarie truſt: But though their offences are<note n="*" place="margin">Equidem cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderim (ſi libet divinare) peccaſse eos infidelitate vel in Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, vel in bona, aut luxurioſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digendo aut ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rè in ſuum emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumentum deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vando. <hi>Pere. ubi ſupra.</hi>
                     </note> uncertaine, yet (no queſtion) they were great; great againſt a King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> whoſe name being alwayes<note n="*" place="margin">Pet. Mart. in Gen.</note> 
                     <hi>Pharaoh à vindicando,</hi> from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, might no ſooner conſider himſelfe, than inflict a puniſhment; a puniſhment not to be ſatisfied by the one, without loſſe of life; and therefore, in all likelyhood, not to be releaſed to the other, without the mediation of powerfull meanes.</p>
                  <p n="15">15 Whereupon, ſince it is certaine this great Officer had offended; that he was caſt from his Office, that he was reſtored againe, and that his meanes of reſtoring is uncertaine; the moſt will thinke the beſt conjecture is, that either his money, or his friends, or both, was the Key which opened the Doore both of the Priſon and his Office. And if money, or friends, were the meanes; who can thinke, he would not ſtrive to regaine the one (his money) the beſt helpe at a dead lift; and ſtudie to obſerve the other (his friends) though not by way of thankfulneſſe, yet to prevent a ſecond diſpleaſure: and being thus prepared, he might well take <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Petition into a ſecond conſideration, and yet never remember <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but forget him.</p>
                  <p n="16">16 For <hi>firſt,</hi> the <hi>maine thing</hi> requeſted, is onely to be brought out of that Houſe, the Priſon; a ſmall matter in it ſelfe, a naturall deſire of freedome and libertie: it can be no pleaſure for one man to ſee another periſh, every man will lend his helping hand, when he may not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger himſelfe. No queſtion, in this reſpect, the chiefe Butler was willing to remember <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> and the rather, becauſe common policie hath taught wicked men (by the example of <hi>Abſolon</hi>) to be juſt and charitable in ſmall matters,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> the better to palliate their injuſtice and oppreſſion in greater affaires.</p>
                  <p>But looking upon this Petition like one of <hi>Pharaohs wiſe Counſellors,</hi> hee findes the <hi>meanes</hi> withall required,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 19.11.</note>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:4863:23"/> beares a high and loftie diſtance from the <hi>end;</hi> which might be obtained a neerer way, without ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, without moving the King, even by the ordinarie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and proceeding of that Gouernment, were the end as it ſeemed at firſt, a matter of ſmall importance: And this great diſproportion betwixt the <hi>end</hi> and the <hi>meanes,</hi> calls the <hi>reaſons</hi> in queſtion.</p>
                  <p n="17">17 Whereof the <hi>firſt</hi> is, that he was <hi>ſtolne out of the Land of the Hebrewes:</hi> Whereat this great Officer (wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make much of a ſmall matter for his owne ends, or elſe no <hi>Aegyptian</hi>) thinkes it wiſedome to pawſe: for ſo being an <hi>Hebrew,</hi> a ſtranger, he might be a Spy, (being a man of worth) he might be ſent of purpoſe (as <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archite,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> 
                     <hi>Davids</hi> friend was, to attend <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>) even to wait upon ſome eminent perſon, ſuch as <hi>Potiphar:</hi> firſt, to make a difference betwixt him and his Wife, the better to defeat his counſels, to deſcry his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections; and ſo by little and little to diſcover the weakeneſſe of the countrey, the affaires of State, the factions of great men, the inclinations of the people, the difference of all; and ſo (by hatching conſpiracies, and breeding ſedition) make way for the deſignes of a forraine enemie: In which caſe (no queſtion) it was much better to keepe him ſtill in priſon, than to procure his libertie; for treaſons and conſpiracies may be long in working, long in contriving, and therefore they may be long in diſcoverie: otherwiſe that cannot be found (which is moſt neceſſarie) the largeneſſe of the Plot, and the number of offenders. This ſeemes to be <hi>Joſephs</hi> owne practice, after his promotion; when purpoſely taking his brethren for Spies,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.</note> he cauſed <hi>Simeon</hi> to be bound, till the reſt (by bringing their youngeſt brother) ſhould prove themſelves honeſt men.</p>
                  <p n="18">18 But no ſuch thing is recorded againſt <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſince his comming into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> nothing of that nature laid to his charge, in the ſpace of thirteene yeeres nothing ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; if it were, yet many things may be ſuſpected,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4863:23"/> without reaſon: For reſolution whereof, the beſt way is to looke backe upon the generalitie of his former cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſee, Is it likely that he had any gall in his heart, any fire-brand in his taile; is it likely that he came to ſport himſelfe in the waters of trouble, rather than to aſſwage them, who like an innocent Dove brought an <hi>Olive branch</hi> in his mouth, and made all things proſper whereſoever he came? And therefore it is more likely (as he himſelfe ſaith) that he was <hi>ſtolne out of the Land of the Hebrewes;</hi> and that from ſome great perſon, and that for revealing faults done by others, unworthy of their ſervice and his owne ſilence. And if ſo (as indeed it was) the denyall is given by himſelfe: for this great Officer, one of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, (not of his minde) a Heatheniſh Politician, willing (no queſtion) to offend againe in the midſt of <hi>Aegyptian</hi> darkeneſſe (a faire opportunitie) and being carefull, <hi>ne quid invidiae ſubiret</hi> (as <hi>Calvin</hi> obſerves) leſt he ſhould derive any envie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe from his owne countreymen (who of all things cannot endure the command of ſtrangers) thinks it no<note n="*" place="margin">Ne forte in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitionem incurrat quaſi vellet man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio contempto magis quàm om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſapientibus Regis patrocinari. <hi>Pare.</hi>
                     </note> wiſedome, to give him freedome, encouragement, or any opportunity to ſhew himſelfe, much leſſe to make mention of him to <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> whoſe worth (caſting a light upon future events, by a rare kinde of divination from Heaven) is moſt likely (like <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod) to over-top the Magicians of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to over-looke and diſparage their practiſes; moſt likely to diſcover preſent offences (at leaſt offences like thoſe in his owne caſe, Lying, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, Colluſion, Partialitie, Oppreſſion, the <hi>leane ill-favoured Kine</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſees not but in a Dreame) and by innocence turne Informer: and the rather, becauſe this innocence is ſo much proteſted in his other reaſon; <hi>And here alſo have I done nothing, why they ſhould put me into the Dungeon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="19">19 And will <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſtill proteſt his innocence? Then (it ſeemes) he will not take the blame upon himſelfe, and confeſſe that fault whereof he was never guiltie, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4863:24"/> preſerve <hi>Potiphars</hi> reputation and his Wives: Like thoſe ſervants, who wittingly and willingly marry themſelves to their Maſters Adulterie, to prevent his publike and approaching ſhame; betray their owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, to patronize his errors, Whoredome, Injuſtice, Oppreſſion, Briberie, and the like: It ſeemes he will not cry,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.14.</note> 
                     <hi>peace, peace, where there is no peace:</hi> And this may be ſomething which makes him leſſe regarded, as one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to be of thoſe thriving profeſſions; either a Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar for another mans luſt, who diſclaimes his owne; or a Broker for anothers griping covetouſneſſe, who will not purchaſe his owne libertie, to be accounted diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; altogether unlikely to winke at offences, and flatter the perverſe counſels of others, who will not for his owne ſake,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.20.</note> in a caſe of ſo great importance, ſpeake <hi>evill</hi> of good, or <hi>good</hi> of evill. And therefore, if he were ſent for out of the Dungeon, more likely with the Prophet <hi>Michaiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.</note> to be ſent thither againe, much more to be kept there, even there to be fed with <hi>bread and water of affliction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="20">20 But this ſomething is not all; the conſequence is greater: for though here's no formall complaint, yet here's one included; the more innocent <hi>Ioſeph</hi> makes himſelfe, the more unjuſt hee makes <hi>Potiphar,</hi> the more unchaſte his Wife: and then to helpe him, to ſhew him any kindneſſe upon tearmes of innocence, and favour a good cauſe, much more to make mention of him to the King, either for favour, in reſpect of his worth, or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, in reſpect of his cauſe; is the next way to bring the whole buſineſſe upon the Stage; the next way, to ſhew <hi>Pharaoh</hi> how much his power hath beene uſed (thereby abuſed) without a courſe of juſtice, ſevere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment inflicted, without a triall; the next way to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thoſe friends who procured his libertie; the next way to recall his owne former faults to a ſecond exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, who is ſo active in other mens: at leaſt, the next way to incenſe and breake all correſpondencie with <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiphar,</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:4863:24"/> a man greater than himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Captaine of the Guard</hi> in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe; who, as formerly, by vertue of his place, hee had committed the chiefe Butler to priſon; ſo now, by diſpleaſure, hee might returne him thither againe, if either he ſhould doe any thing in that buſineſſe without his notice, or not fawne, and applaud, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the partialitie of his proceedings againſt <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> For ſome there are, that <hi>make a man an offender for a word, that lay a ſnare for him that reproveth in the Gate, and turne aſide the juſt for a thing of naught, Eſay</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 21. Much more might <hi>Potiphar</hi> be diſpleaſed, if ſuch a buſineſſe ſhould be mentioned to the King, which ſo neerely reflects upon his Wives incontinence, and his owne injuſtice.</p>
                  <p n="21">21 But admit <hi>Potiphar</hi> were of himſelfe as eaſie to be entreated for <hi>Ioſephs</hi> libertie, as he was formerly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to impriſon him; yet the frequent and private ſolicitations of a Wife, being ſo often the impediments of juſtice, in the diſtribution both of favours and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, but eſpecially the malice of an <hi>imperious who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh woman,</hi> ſo farre beyond expreſſion, and her condition ſo apt to be a buſie-body in the affaires of others, much more to be active about her owne; more eſpecially, when thoſe affaires behold the preſentment of her inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate deſires, <hi>ſpretaeque injuriam formae;</hi> and (which moſt of all ſtirres up to revenge) the former contempt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of her luſt: theſe particulars (all of them drawne from a lying tongue, which I am ſure <hi>hateth thoſe who are afflicted by it, Prov.</hi> 26. I ſay, theſe) are weapons which perhaps the chiefe Butler had rather ſharpen than oppoſe; as knowing that a woman, <hi>aut vehementer amat, aut capitaliter odit,</hi> is either the beſt friend, or the greateſt enemie; and ſo in this caſe (having once before deluded her Husband) moſt likely to urge his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to the utmoſt, and that more againſt him, the chiefe Butler, than <hi>Joſeph;</hi> as having leſſe oportunitie, fewer wayes to encreaſe the puniſhment of a poore priſoner,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4863:25"/> than to be revenged of his friend, a great Officer in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, and that reſtored to his Office: And ſurely, it is likely, that ſhee, whoſe craftie wilineſſe ſo well ſucceeded to make advantage of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Garment (which indeed was her ſhame) would afterwards take upon her both to know her friends, and oppreſſe her enemies.</p>
                  <p n="22">22 Nay, further to ſearch the depth of this <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> wiſedome, before we turne it into fooliſhneſſe, and (as it were) to plead for him freely, who would not ſo much as remember another, no, not by the ſtrongeſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of life, libertie, and honour. 'Tis true, the ſtory tells us, that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had the managing of all things in the Priſon, and was in particular charged by <hi>Potiphar</hi> with the keeping of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſervants, two great offenders; whereby it might be preſumed, he had at that time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masked the ſhameleſſe countenance of his Wife, which made him ſo confident in the care of an old ſervant; a ſtrong motive (no doubt) to encourage others to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate his further enlargement: yet the chiefe Butler, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored Officer, knowes perhaps by experience, or feares, that <hi>Potiphar</hi> may be like <hi>Entrapelus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ep. l. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> of whom <hi>Horace</hi> ſpeakes:
<q>
                        <l>— Cuicunque nocere volebat</l>
                        <l>Veſtimenta dabat pretioſa.</l>
                     </q> One, whoſe favours were like the faire words of <hi>Iael</hi> to <hi>Siſera;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 4.18, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Come in (my Lord) feare not, come in:</hi> like her <hi>Bottle of Milke,</hi> and her <hi>Covering,</hi> which lull'd the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine aſleepe, and made him ſecure of her protection; who thereby contrived and effected the glory of his finall overthrow: And ſo (indeed) <hi>Ioſeph</hi> might be put into Office (as <hi>Haman</hi> was invited by Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> to the Banquet) not ſo much for favour, as hatred.</p>
                  <p>Imployed hee was: but this might be of purpoſe, to divert him from contriving other matters of greater conſequence, anſwerable to his worth; at leaſt from ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying the meanes of libertie, and the remedie of his falſe impriſonment.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:4863:25"/>
                  <p>Nay, imployed hee was (as formerly in all likelyhood by the connivencie) ſo now by<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.</note> ſpeciall appointment of <hi>Potiphar:</hi> but, <hi>timeo Danaos &amp; dona ferentes,</hi> this might be, not ſo much in approbation of his fidelitie, as to make him depend upon his further kindneſſe, the kindneſſe of an adverſarie; which wee know no ſooner turnes grievances into hopes, than hopes into folly: a Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of cloſe oppreſſion, and the readie way to <hi>Ioſephs ne ultra,</hi> his continuall bondage.</p>
                  <p>And thus likewiſe (to the ſame purpoſe) his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar imployment might be, not ſo much an Office to keepe others, as a ſnare to catch himſelfe: For ſo, by taking opportunitie to eſcape without any tryall at all, (which perhaps was chiefely deſired, as being moſt for their credit who firſt impriſoned him) or by running into errors (as no man is ſufficient to prevent all) his adverſaries might finde holes in that Coat which had none before, and have ſomething whereof to accuſe him; at leaſt (by ſhewing him a little kindneſſe, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of a Priſon, and a command within it) the better diſcover who were moſt likely to be his friends, their enemies, and durſt any way comply with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> without <hi>Potiphars</hi> conſent.</p>
                  <p n="23">23 And ſurely, if that be true which<note n="*" place="margin">In vit. Agric.</note> 
                     <hi>Tacitus</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>proprium humani ingenii eſt odiſſe quem laeſeris,</hi> That we are prone by the jealouſie of a corrupt nature, to hate that man alwayes, whom once we purpoſely hurt: then (no queſtion) if it were publikely knowne, that <hi>Potiphar</hi> were ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Coniugis amori plus aequo tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens. <hi>Ioſeph. l. 1. Antiq.</hi>
                     </note> unjuſt, as to impriſon <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Inaudita cauſa, inexplorata fide veri, tanquam reus criminis in carcerem Ioſeph mittitur. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
                     </note> without hearing him ſpeake in his owne defence at firſt, and without calling him to account afterwards, (as here's no examination upon divine record) it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be imagined, but that <hi>Potiphar</hi> will be ſtill unjuſt: and in this reſpect, the chiefe Butler, his ſervant alſo; nay (forſooth) his ſervants ſervant, to ſecond his deſires, to keepe <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſtill in darkeneſſe; for feare his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence ſhould <hi>breake forth as the Noone-day,</hi> and (like that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4863:26"/> fire from Heaven for which <hi>Elias</hi> prayed) conſume the Captaine and his men.<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="24">24 Or, if the truth were manifeſt to <hi>Potiphar,</hi> and he really inclin'd to releaſe this priſoner; yet the chiefe Butler (meaſuring others by himſelfe) thinkes that <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiphar,</hi> ſo great a man, would at leaſt ſeeme wiſe and juſt in the eyes of his Prince, and not have others meddle with his faults, or ſo much as ſeeme to know any paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of that nature; that (being <hi>Captaine of the Guard,</hi> a man moſt likely to be powerfull in the State, or of a proud ſpirit) he will take his owne private courſes to enlarge <hi>Ioſeph</hi> by little and little, and not returne the ſame publike way, by which he proceeded againſt him; never recant, never confeſſe his errors before men, and ſet the ſaddle upon the right horſe; but either bridle the tongue, and ſtop the mouth of truth, or breake the necke of him that ſpeakes it.</p>
                  <p>And that for this purpoſe: As the chiefe Prieſts in the 28. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> gave large money to ſouldiers to belye the Reſurrection; and withall promiſed, <hi>if this came to the Governours eares,</hi> they <hi>would perſwade him, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them</hi> (a helliſh policie) not onely reward, but ſecure and protect the lyars: So hee (Captaine of the Guard, ſo neere the perſon of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) wants no opportunitie to open and cloſe up the Princes eares, for his owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; he wants no money to bribe, whoſe eſtate was lately ſo proſperous, for <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſake; and (by the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his Office) he wants no ſouldiers or warlike men, under his owne command, to out-brave the truth, to ſpit in the face of innocence, and upon the leaſt occaſion to fight, eſpecially in a Womans quarrell, and that when there is ſo little feare of being called in queſtion; and above all, ſo much hope to caſt lots for <hi>Ioſephs</hi> garment, and weare their Miſtreſſe favour: ſuch, and ſuch like va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities being too often greater motives of courage, than Religion and a good cauſe.</p>
                  <p n="25">25 Howſoever, ſince the maintaining of correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4863:26"/> amongſt great perſons lookes many wayes, and that upon trifles too, ſtudying and obſerving them more than better things; we may well conjecture, that as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> were m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de friends,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.12.</note> by agreeing together againſt that innocent Lambe, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> ſo theſe two Officers will continue friends, brethren in evill, rather than Authoritie ſhall be truly informed, and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred.</p>
                  <p>And thus it may be, this <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Courtier degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from the Religion of his Countrey, and reflecting wholly upon himſelfe, having (as he thinkes) made all the uſe he can of ſuch a friend (but an Interpreter) whoſe worth is ſeldome eſteemed or thought on, unleſſe it be for diſcourſe, or in caſes of extremitie, (beſides, finding at firſt no faire way open, competible with his owne private ends, to ſpeake in a poore priſoners behalfe) might afterwards ſoone forget <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and lay aſide the memorie of his Petition, to verifie the Proverbe, <hi>Out of ſight, out of minde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="26">26 But let this cautelous <hi>Aegyptian</hi> pretend what wiſedome he can to excuſe himſelfe, all is not ſufficient to free him (though but a Heathen) from this heavie cenſure, much leſſe can it free a Chriſtian upon like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: for ſurely, in private affaires (the onely ſcope of this Text) no policie can be good againſt that charitie o juſtice whereunto wee are entreated by Petition, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nnocence, bound by thankefulneſſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited by many fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re opportunities, in regard there ſeemes no reaſon (u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r favo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) why the ſame ſpirit which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the rending of <hi>Samuels</hi> garment to the fatall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and deſtruction of <hi>Saul,</hi> in his owne audience,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> and yet found no diſcouragement, ſhould not with like ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe tell <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or <hi>Potiphar</hi> at leaſt, the truth of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>Ioſephs</hi> garment, and the danger of not reſtoring it, without blemiſh to the owner.</p>
                  <p n="27">27 And yet amongſt men-pleaſers, there is a worldly policie, which thinkes it better to bow and reverence
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4863:27"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:4863:27"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:4863:28"/> to <hi>Haman,</hi> better to <hi>conſent with the Thiefe, and to have fellowſhip with the deceitfull,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal</hi> 50.18. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 28.25.</note> even ſuch as have made <hi>lyes their refuge, and under falſehood have hid themſelves;</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to comply and hold correſpondencie with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked practiſes of many great men, who (in the words of the Pſalmiſt) <hi>cruelly,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.20.</note> 
                     <hi>diſdainefully, deſpightfully ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the righteous,</hi> rather than <hi>call for juſtice, or plead for truth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 59. <hi>v.</hi> 4. rather than <hi>judge the fatherleſſe,</hi> ſpeake for the Widow, or <hi>relieve the oppreſſed,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his worth, though his cauſe be innocent, and his deſerts beyond compare. <hi>Hoc aulicorum ſolenne eſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidè inſontes prodere, &amp; potius tradere jugulandos quàm ut offendant cos à quibus metuunt</hi> (ſaith learned <hi>Calvin</hi>) This is the propertie of time-ſerving Courtiers, perfidiouſly to betray the innocent, nay, to expoſe them to a finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, rather than offend thoſe whom they thinke may croſſe their deſignes, or prevent their ambition. <hi>Davids</hi> experience found out not onely the truth, but the ſlyneſſe alſo of theſe proceedings:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.11.</note> 
                     <hi>I became</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a reproach to mine enemies, but eſpecially to my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and they of my acquaintance were afraid of me, and conueyed themſelves from me.</hi> This experience of <hi>David</hi> was a prediction of Chriſt, and verified at his Paſſion: for when hee was apprehended, behold his Diſciples <hi>forſooke him, and fled, Mar.</hi> 14, 50. Nay, <hi>Peter,</hi> that great profeſſor of fidelitie,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.54.</note> 
                     <hi>followed him a farre off</hi> as though it were a ſhame, a diſadvantage to be a follower of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> who ſpent not onely his breath, but his moſt precious bloud, to redeeme him and all mankinde from an everlaſting bondage: as though it were no religious courage, but a deſperate reſolution, which made Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> petition King <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> for the lives of her people, when the ſucceſſe both for them and her ſelfe was ſo doubtfull,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heſt.</hi> 4. 16.</note> ſo full of diſtraction; <hi>If I periſh, I periſh:</hi> as though, <hi>exeat aula qui volet eſſe pius</hi> it were a like Orthodox, to flye from the love and protection, as to have fallen from the ſtate of innocence: as though
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4863:28"/> there were no <hi>Wine-preſse of wrath</hi> to be trodden by feet which never <hi>ſwell;</hi> no divine juſtice,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30.33.</note> no <hi>breath of the Lord (like a ſtreame of Brimſtone)</hi> to kindle the fire of eternall perdition for thoſe fawning flattering Paraſites, who obſcure and hide the Lampe of innocence under a <hi>Buſhell,</hi> and will not ſet it upon the <hi>Table,</hi> to enlighten both themſelves and others; but rather (like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Churles) <hi>deviſe wicked devices to deſtroy the poore with lying words, even when the needie ſpeaketh right, Eſay</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p n="28">28 Thus it may be the reaſons of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Petition were by this great <hi>Aegyptian</hi> (one of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> wiſe counſellers, or rather thoſe <hi>Senatours</hi> to whom <hi>Ioſeph</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards taught better <hi>wiſedome</hi>) turn'd into arguments of denyall and forgetfulneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="29">29 But had <hi>Joſephs</hi> complaint (ſuch as it is) beene a welcome meſſage to <hi>Potiphar,</hi> or <hi>Potiphar</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> men of equall condition, the buſineſſe (in all likelyhood) had not ended in generall tearmes, nor after ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and beene ſmothered in a Dungeon: No, if with<note n="*" place="margin">Ad primum ingratitudinis gradum pertinet quòd aliquis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribuat mala pro bonis. <hi>Aqu. 22.107.2. c.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Aquinas</hi> there be a kinde of unthankfulneſſe (as, I am ſure there is, a common practice) which returnes evill for good, even <hi>hatred for good will;</hi> then it ſtands not with the policie of an <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> to forget any paſſages of ſtrife and contention, but rather to urge a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſcoverie, and to make advantage of a difference, (as here, by remembring <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and the reaſons of his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition) for ſo by giving private intelligence, or by decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe in publike, (not ſo much for the truth, as the poſſibilitie of his owne private ends) he might (as it were) begge more familiar acquaintance, and skrue himſelfe into the favour of the one, by the deſtruction of the other: like thoſe deceitfull workers amongſt us, thoſe ſlye companions, who (under the colour of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) goe up and downe, inſinuating themſelves into the counſels and reſolutions of different judgements, to betray one, and flatter another; the very off-ſpring of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4863:29"/> 
                     <hi>Dalilah,</hi> the ſeed of the Whore, whoſe faire words made <hi>Samſon</hi> diſcover where his ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h lay,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.</note> to his owne deſtruction. But great men being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h to heare of their faults, and ſeldome or never admitting poore men to an open conteſtation, but where the caſe is very plaine (or made ſo) on their owne ſides; <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Petition wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting opportunitie to be ſeconded, at leaſt to be importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (the hopes many times, and endeavours too, of an u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt Iudge) is here thought beſt anſwered by ſilence, his condition ſlighted, himſelfe forgot.</p>
                  <p n="30">30 Had <hi>Ioſeph</hi> neither worth nor innocence to plead his cauſe; Then (me thinkes) the ordinarie courſe of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice might have thought him more fit for the place of execution, than to continue in a Dungeon.</p>
                  <p>Had <hi>Ioſeph, corpus ſine pectore,</hi> a groſſe body, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any active worth, or abilities of minde, but onely this innocence of life, a bare ſimplicitie of converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Then likewiſe hee might have beene releaſed too, without much prejudice to the cauſe of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment (as wanting judgement to underſtand and maintaine the reaſon of his libertie) in which caſe, it muſt needes be more trouble than advantage to keepe ſo poore a priſoner, much better to have his roome than his companie.</p>
                  <p>Had <hi>Ioſeph</hi> abundance of worth, enterlined with ſome malevolent qualitie;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note> a <hi>forme of godlineſſe, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the power thereof;</hi> Had hee beene a malefactor upon record, or committed ſome hainous offence, not yet anſwered before authoritie; Had hee beene poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with any raging ſpirit of ambition, or revenge; but otherwiſe, a man of great ſufficiencie, enriched with many parts and perfections both of Nature and Art, no leſſe able than willing to ſatisfie their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; who ſaid <hi>unto the Seers, ſee not; and unto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, prophecie not unto us right things, ſpeake ſmooth things, prophecie deceits; Eſay</hi> 30. <hi>v.</hi> 10. Oh, then the policie of an <hi>Aegyptian</hi> would have ſtudied to ſhew
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4863:29"/> this man kindneſſe, earneſtly entreated his releaſe, as the Iewes did for <hi>Barabbas;</hi> nay,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.40.</note> preferred him too perhaps (were the times as afterwards) to be ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere oppreſſing Task-maſter over the people; as being the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tteſt inſtrument for unworthy deſignes, who is himſelfe lyable to exception, moſt likely to make a time-ſerver, who every morning feares a day of tryall in his owne caſe; moſt likely (in a womans judgement) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe innocent <hi>Naboth,</hi> who is himſelfe a <hi>ſonne of Belial;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.10.</note> moſt likely to out-face the proceedings of Law and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who knowes his owne free-hold may be juſtly called in queſtion; moſt likely to blow the coales of ſedition, to kindle and encreaſe the fire of a divelliſh doctrine, whoſe <hi>conſcience</hi> is alreadie <hi>ſeared with a hot iron,</hi> branded with impietie, made famous by impenitencie.</p>
                  <p>But here innocence of life, and thoſe rare abilities of minde, wiſedome, and diſcretion, (confeſſed afterwards by <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) kiſſe each other,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.39.</note> and are met together in one and the ſame perſon, <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> and therefore no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, if he be not remembred in a ſtrange and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh countrey: For,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.14.</note> where <hi>Iudgement is turned away backward, and Iuſtice ſtands afarre off, when Truth is fallen in the ſtreetes, and Equitie cannot enter;</hi> there (I am ſure) hee that proteſteth innocence, even hee that <hi>departeth from evill, maketh himſelfe a prey; Eſay</hi> 59. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p n="31">31 But admit the reaſons free from all exception, as well for the ſafetie of the one, as the innocence of the other; and that, being in priſon, there was no offence ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the want of <hi>flattering Titles,</hi> which (like a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face indeed) ſome men obſerve and weigh more than the whole matter beſides: yet the kindneſſe here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted (eſpecially to move the King) is a favour too high to be reached by a man of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> condition; for he is but an <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſervant, a priſoner, unwilling by his innocence, unable by his povertie, to ſecond his Petition with a Bribe: but the chiefe Butler is an <hi>Aegyptian,</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:4863:30"/> who cannot as yet reade (as it was afterwards prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied hee ſhould) nor underſtand <hi>the language of Canaan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 14.18.</note> unleſſe it be <hi>Apples of Gold in pictures of Silver;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.11.</note> a Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphick of this nature is proper for his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; a temptation very powerfull, and no leſſe ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable at all times: being a great Officer, and that reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Office, either by his money or his friends, he thinkes he may well make the beſt of his Place; ſell deare (as he bought) the very lees of favour, either for preſent money, greater imployment, or the cuſtome of more ſuiters, to re-ſupply his ſtore, and advance his condition in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe; where <hi>every man</hi> being <hi>a friend to him that giveth gifts, Prov.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 6. 'tis likely the cry of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> the voice of that <hi>Charmer,</hi> is ſeldome heard, <hi>charme he never ſo wiſely,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.5.</note> who makes the words of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> an introduction to his requeſt, <hi>Silver and Gold have I none.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 3.6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="32">32 But had this <hi>Aegyptian</hi> beene within the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of doing good workes, he might have been taught otherwiſe; that though hee (who having many Suites of his owne depending upon the Kings favour, will not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſpeake for other men) may well deſerve the Lawrell for his paines, even that, engraven &amp; ſtampt upon the princely front of bleſſed memorie; yet <hi>Ioſeph</hi> muſt be remembred with a Cup of Bleſſing, though he cannot pay for it; and that all kind of favors towards all ſorts of men, are not to be ſold ſo publikely, ſo certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as Wine is by a Buſh, leſt children and paſſengers turne it to a Proverbe, <hi>Here a Buſh and there a Theefe:</hi> For as there is a thankefulneſſe which is not written in Letters of Gold, a thankefulneſſe performed (ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas) per exhibitionem honoris &amp; reverentiae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">22. <hi>q.</hi> 106. 3. 5.</note> by giving honour and reverence;<note place="margin">22. <hi>q.</hi> 107.1.2.</note> nay, <hi>ad debitum gratitudinis red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum ſufficit ſola voluntas</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author:) for want of other meanes to be thankefull, the will is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; much more, when the tongue is the pen, and the knee the poſture of a gratefull minde: ſo there is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4863:30"/> written in Letters of Marble, binding the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an for ever, in the 11. of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> to <hi>caſt his bread upon the waters;</hi> even there to ſhew kindneſſe, where there is no poſſibilitie of requitall: and yet this muſt be held a ſpeciall kinde of providence, and a meanes of great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, according to that of <hi>Seneca;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sen. in Prov.</note> 
                     <hi>Habet in adverſis auxilia, qui in proſperis commodat:</hi> Which in effect is well tranſlated, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.17. <hi>He that hath pitie on the poore, lendeth to the Lord; and looke what he hath given him, he will repay:</hi> even He, the riches of whoſe mercie cannot but make charitable men great gainers: But where men are of hard uncircumciſed hearts and eares, no mervaile if favours be not freely beſtowed, nor any good fortune told by an <hi>Aegyptian Gipſey</hi> to him who is not open-handed.</p>
                  <p n="33">33 Indeed, had <hi>Ioſephs</hi> freedome beene thought a worke of as laſting fame, as now the contrarie proves of infamie; then it may be this <hi>Aegyptian</hi> would have diſpenſed a little with his greedie-griping hand, to get himſelfe a Name; then (according to his place) upon <hi>Pharaohs</hi> birth-day at the furtheſt, like the Water-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit upon great ſolemnities, hee would have ſent forth Wine to fill the Dungeon; then perhaps his Wine (I meane, the Fees) nay, the Bribes, and exactions of his Office, ſhould have overflowne into thoſe pleaſant ſtreames of bountie which run amongſt the ſtonie Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyes, and there have erected ſome famous Altar (as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did, in memorie of <hi>Pompeys</hi> defeat) or built ſome religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Temple for the ſervice of this rare Interpreter, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents anſwerable to the ancient practice and vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory of that Nation: but not underſtanding the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe (the meaning) of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> name, nor being able to fore-ſee a change, this ſtrange event, either for qualitie or durance; hee ſeemes onely to verifie that in effect, (which is too common in theſe dayes) that <hi>wealth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth many friends, but the poore man is ſeparated from his neighbour, Prov.</hi> 19.4.</p>
                  <p n="34">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4863:31"/>34 And yet when we conſider the particular condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this chiefe Butler, I ſhould thinke the ſtrength of new Wine had broken this old Veſſell, overcome his memorie, made him weake in judgement, careleſſe both of himſelfe and others, (as many are upon like occaſions) making his <hi>belly his God;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19.</note> regarding the goodneſſe of his Wine, the curioſitie of his taſte, more than the encreaſe or preſervation of his eſtate: at leaſt ſtudying the newneſſe of his Bottles, the particular duties of his Office, more than the reaſons of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Petition.</p>
                  <p n="35">35 Or I ſhould thinke this <hi>Aegyptian Ganimede</hi> (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a manner as many opportunities to move the King, as the King had occaſion to drinke in the ſpace of two yeeres) I ſay, I ſhould thinke him willing of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to remember his fellow priſoner; but (in that hee was the chiefe and principall of his ranke) having his kindneſſe too much ſwayed, or his remembrance tyed to the pleaſure and approbation of ſome inferiour Officers, ſome unworthy ſervants, who (if they cannot by ſome ſtrict covenant diſpoſe their maſters free or juſt intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to their owne ſpeciall advantage) will maliciouſly ſtudie either to divert or delay them; ſuch maſters (one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too credulous) being like blinde men, led and guided by their Dogs; not ſuch as licked the ſores of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but whoſe <hi>tongues are a ſharpe ſword,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.4. <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.5.</note> who <hi>bite with their teeth, and cry peace; and hee who putteth not into their mouthes, even they prepare warre againſt him,</hi> lying, and ſlandering,<note place="margin">Lingua mali pars peſſima ſervi.</note> and back-biting, and evill ſurmiſes, the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible tokens of a peſtilent and malicious heart: againſt which, there is no better remedy, no weapon of defence, or prevention better, than what was ſpoken upon other occaſions, either <hi>Pauls</hi> caveat, <hi>Beware of Dogs, Phil.</hi> 3.2. or <hi>Davids</hi> prayer, in the 22. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the 19. and 20. Verſes, <hi>Be not thou farre from me, O Lord, haſte thee to helpe me, deliver my ſoule from the ſword, and my Darling from the power of the Dog;</hi> my condition, from <hi>ſerving
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4863:31"/> a man more unworthy than my ſelfe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccl.</hi> 25.8.</note> and as with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremiah, from the houſe of Ionathan the Scribe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 37.20.</note> ſo from all peculiar relation to thoſe <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> who are like <hi>Reedes ſhaken with the winde,</hi> or like <hi>Winde,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.7. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.11.</note> wherein <hi>the Lord is not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="36">36 But as the Text is plaine, the chiefe Butler him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe did not put <hi>Ioſephs teares into his Bottles,</hi> did not remember him: ſo (leaving other conjectures to the libertie of application) it is very probable from the conſequence of the ſtory, that this forgetfulneſſe was grounded upon deepe premeditation, and chiefely drawne from the reaſons of <hi>Joſephs</hi> Petition: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when he was forced (as afterwards) to ſpeake of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.</note> with making mention of his owne impriſonment, hee would have better remembred the greatneſſe of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> miſerie, the excellencie of his<note n="*" place="margin">Commemorat interpretationem Ioſephi, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m non laudat ſed vocat puerum, ſervum principis lanio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Parcus.</hi>
                     </note> worth, the modeſtie of his Petition, the innocence and juſtneſſe of his cauſe; he would have given a better te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of his fellow priſoner, and more commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than hee did; at leaſt, hee would have requeſted (<note n="*" place="margin">Pro Ioſepho ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil conſulit aut rogat, ut accerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à Rege. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </note> what he did not) that <hi>Joſeph</hi> might have beene ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for out of the Dungeon; a paſſage obſerved by Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, arguing a ſtudied neglect; and that he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, rather than his owne countrymen, the Magicians of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> ſhould be diſparaged by an <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſervant, or <hi>Potiphar</hi> diſpleaſed, for taking a poore priſoners part; rather than offences ſhould be in danger of diſcoverie, or innocence in the way of protection, <hi>Ioſephs</hi> miſerie ſhould be ſtill prolonged, his worth eclipſed, his Petition ſuppreſſed, and his owne part in this act (never to be forgotten) ſhould be neither Wine, nor thankes for this Interpreter; but onely ingratitude, <hi>Seminarium ſcelerum omnium,</hi> the Seminarie of all vices, baſe unthankfulneſſe, and that in the higheſt degree: for, <hi>Ingratiſſimus omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt qui oblitus eſt,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) He is moſt ungratefull of all others, who will not remember his friend, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get him.</p>
                  <p n="37">
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:4863:32"/>37 It ſeemes the chiefe Butler forgot what hee was before; in being releaſed from one extreame, he quickly falls into another,<note place="margin">Non potuit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordari Carceris &amp; interpretis ſui propterea quod recuperatae dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitati plus aequo incubuit. <hi>Muſc.</hi>
                     </note> and there moſt properly ſhewes as well the ſeverall kindes and poſtures, as the nakedneſſe of a forgetfull minde: For before, hee was in priſon, ſhrunke (as it were) and contracted with the ſadneſſe of adverſitie; but now hee is in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, blowne and puffed up with the pride of proſperitie, <hi>quem homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſtatum ſuperbia comitatur &amp; aliorum contemptus,</hi> a ſtate uſually attended with pride, and the contempt of others; whereunto (as wee read) all <hi>Aegyptians</hi> are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſubject; though he carry the ſame body, yet he hath not the ſame wits about him.</p>
                  <p>Before (being in priſon) he ſaw a propheticall ſpirit, the crowne of his rejoycing, clothed in ragges, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to approach the royall preſence, without firſt changing his apparrell,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.</note> and ſhaving his haire; but now (being in the Kings houſe) hee judgeth every mans worth by the ſoftneſſe of his rayment, by the goodneſſe of his clothes, by the rare and dayly handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft of his Barber.</p>
                  <p>Before, hee was glad to embrace all correſpondencie with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.</note> his Keeper, though like another <hi>Lazarus,</hi> lying at the Gate-houſe, begging reliefe; thinking this <hi>poore man</hi> as able by his wiſdome <hi>to deliver a whole Citie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.15.</note> as by ſuch ſtrange revelation to fore-tell his happineſſe: but now, being in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, <hi>curia pauperibus clauſa eſt,</hi> he ſhuts the doores of favour, and will not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (not within forſooth) to <hi>remember this poore man;</hi> thinking (perhaps) none worthy to be ſpoken to in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar manner, much leſſe to be mentioned to the King, who are not like himſelfe, filled with the Wine-pots, and fed with the <hi>fleſh-pots of Aegypt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before, from looking ſadly, he lifted up his head at the ſight of <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> but now (ſhould they meete together) me thinkes, he caſts downe his head, and turnes away his eyes from beholding him, as though he were an object
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4863:32"/> more fit for a bended brow, and a ſupercilious looke, than a chearefull countenance.</p>
                  <p>Before, words of a milde and plyable nature were courteouſly enterchanged: but now, the pride of proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie makes him thinke (if occaſion were offered) ſome harſh and bitter ſpeeches, ſome churliſh, inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, blaſpheming language, catching at words before they are halfe ſpoken, and miſtaking the ſenſe, will bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maintaine the diſparitie of his condition, more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and encreaſe the reputation of his place.</p>
                  <p>Before, the ſtill voice of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> interpretation was like the ſound of the Dulcimer, greedily entertained: but now he ſtops his eares, and from the hollow of a Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon will not heare the Eccho of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Petition.</p>
                  <p>Before (though the Scripture thinke it beſt not to name thoſe words, which are but winde) yet (no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſince all <hi>Aegyptians</hi> are obſerved by Hiſtorians to be "braggers, great talkers, and of little truth in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, we may well preſume he made large promiſes of remembrance, and thoſe appearing in the darke and noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Dungeon (like the Starre which guided the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) both credible and comfortable:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.</note> but now (being carried aloft into the freſh aire) <hi>mentitur ſperatum, &amp; promiſſum auxilium,</hi> thoſe promiſes prove like falling Starres, Meteors, which quickly conſume themſelves, and vaniſh into ſmoake; or rather, ſome <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> drawing <hi>Ioſeph</hi> out of his way, turning him aſide, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the direction and favour of other Guides; and now at laſt leaving him to himſelfe, <hi>Major quàm prius deſperatio incumbit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) to wander yet further in the midſt of deſpaire, to continue yet longer in a place of miſerie: <hi>for he did not remember Joſeph, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="38">38 Never conſidering, as <hi>Oleaſter</hi> ſpeakes in his Commentaries upon <hi>Eſay: Qui ab aliquo protectionem ſperat, &amp; non protegitur, ignominia afficitur;</hi> Hee that makes another man hope for favour and protection at
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4863:33"/> his hands, and yet affords none, takes the wiſeſt courſe to worke that mans undoing, ſeemes to ſtudie his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, and cunningly to turne his long expectation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a laſting reproach; in regard all men, in ſuch a caſe, are prone to ſpend their cenſures: ſome, accuſe his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; others, ſuſpect his fidelitie; many blame his confidence, and too many ſcoffe at the vanitie of his hopes; crying, <hi>There, there, ſo would wee have it:</hi> Whereas (indeed) the fault is his; his onely, I meane that counterfeit <hi>Mecaenas,</hi> whoſe faire words and falſe heart hath made it a familiar practice, and judged it the ſafeſt way, <hi>per amici fallere nomen,</hi> to betray his Petitioner with a kiſſe, and to lull him aſleepe with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. Thus, in effect, wee know the Great Maſter himſelfe ſuffered:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.24, 38.</note> and as <hi>the ſervant is not above his Lord,</hi> but muſt <hi>take up his croſse and follow</hi> him; ſo, of all ſervants, the Diſciple, the Interpreter, is moſt likely to be deceived after ſuch a manner, even with words <hi>ſofter than Oile,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.21.</note> 
                     <hi>ſweeter than Honey;</hi> by how much a harmeleſſe nature, buſied with divine contemplations, or oppreſſed with troubles, is ſooneſt ſtained with this<note n="*" place="margin">Credulitas er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror magis eſt, quàm culpa, &amp; quidem in optimi cuiuſque mentem irrepit facillimè. <hi>Cie.</hi>
                     </note> credulitie; not ſo much a crime (ſaith <hi>Tully</hi>) as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon error of the nobleſt minde.</p>
                  <p n="39">39 And indeed (it may be) this <hi>Aegyptian</hi> thinkes <hi>Ioſeph</hi> deſerves no other, but to be ſlighted as a weake man, for being ſo credulous, ſo facile and readie to interprete the happineſſe of his Dreame, without making ſome contract or bargaine before-hand, in his owne behalfe: For there are ſome Ages ſo wiſe in their owne conceits, and ſo frozen with hardneſſe, that to be <hi>a chearefull giver,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</note> to ſhew any kindneſſe, without a covenant, is the next way to be accounted fooliſh, at leaſt to prevent a due requitall. But oh wretched times! to thinke ſuch freedome of minde a prejudice, which in all caſes reflecting upon <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> condition, is an argument of a moſt divine and heavenly diſpoſition: whereas that, <hi>Quid dabitis,</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:4863:33"/> What will you give me, was but the voice of a Harlot, in the 38. of <hi>Geneſis:</hi> And yet ſurely, amongſt us there is a generation of Vipers crept at leaſt into the Patronage of Interpreters, which ſpeake the ſame Language,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.7.</note> and will not <hi>be warned to flee from the wrath to come.</hi> Nay, I feare, this uncharitable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull, ſacrilegious Language, is ſpoken by the tongues not onely of men, but Angels, Angels of the Church, and taught from the Chaire of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; but,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.13.</note> as I muſt <hi>eſteeme them very highly in love,</hi> ſo I ſpare them <hi>for their workes ſake.</hi> Sure I am, ſuch example was never drawne from this rare Interpreter, <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> it might come from <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer: who, as <hi>ſounding Braſse,</hi> or as <hi>a tinckling Cymball,</hi> altogether uncharitable, is more fit for the Bellfrey than the Quier, nay, to be whipped quite out of the Temple, as being alreadie judged by the Spirit of Truth, to be in the <hi>gall of bitterneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 8.23.</note> 
                     <hi>and bond of iniquitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="40">40 And now, though the tediouſneſſe of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe may be a little excuſed from the nature or ſubject of it, <hi>a Court buſineſſe;</hi> wherein a man once engaged, knowes not well when, or how, he ſhall come off: yet ſurely it is high time to make an end of all conjectures; whereof, no doubt, (were there otherwiſe any kinde of demonſtration to be found) the wiſeſt man would be moſt impatient: and yet I have one thing more of like nature, a ſtrange thing (me thinkes) very remarkable, even kindneſſe from this <hi>Aegyptian;</hi> which I cannot omit, becauſe it may be objected, I muſt not paſſe by without ſome acknowledgement: And ſurely, it may be very probable, that (like the craftie Lawyer, who thinkes hee deſerves his Fee, for not being againſt his Client) the chiefe Butler thought it a kindneſſe, nay, a ſufficient favour for <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> if (in ſtead of Wine, which he ſhould give) he did not give him <hi>Vineger to drinke;</hi> if he did not reveale his complaint againſt <hi>Potiphar,</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:4863:34"/> leſt <hi>Potiphar</hi> ſhould encreaſe his puniſhment; if he did not returne a churliſh anſwere,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.</note> as <hi>Nabal</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi> tell <hi>Ioſeph</hi> hee ſpake out of diſcontent, whereunto (though true, like the propheſies of <hi>Caſſandra</hi>) no credit muſt be given; and ſo, by the ſubtletie of oppreſſion, make him leſſe hopefull than before, and a lyar to boot. For ſome wee finde,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15.</note> who loving the <hi>wages of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> in ſtead of compaſſion, encouragement, juſtice, or the due reward of merit, returne <hi>pro perca Scorpium,</hi> for a Fiſh a Serpent deepely ſtinging,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.10.</note> openly inueighing, whiſpering againſt and inſulting over <hi>Ioſephs</hi> conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as one in their judgement contemptible (by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie) of ſmall worth, alwayes a troubleſome ſuiter, unworthy to have his Petition ſigned, unleſſe it be with a greater croſſe;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.8.</note> juſt as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who knew not <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> anſwered that requeſt of the <hi>Iſraelites, Exod.</hi> 5. <hi>Ye are idle, ye are idle; therefore ye ſay, Let us goe and doe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Lord: goe ye now therefore and worke, for there ſhall be no Straw given you, yet ſhall you deliver the tale of Bricks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="41">41 Thus, even thus many times, as the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> complaines in the 123. <hi>Pſalme, verſe</hi> 4. <hi>Our ſoule is filled with the ſcornefull reproofe of the wealthy, and with the deſpightfulneſſe of the proud.</hi> Our ſoule (ſaith hee) not our ſoules; intimating (at leaſt by way of applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that a fellow-feeling charitie turnes all mens ſoules into one, makes them all alike, all but one indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall object of compaſſion: So that, <hi>Homo qui ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini calamitoſo eſt miſericors, meminit ſui;</hi> He who will not remember another, forgets himſelfe; forgets his complaint, of whom <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was a type, the complaint of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.34.</note> for whoſe ſake hee <hi>muſt denie himſelfe;</hi> even that complaint in the 25. of <hi>Matthew: I was hungry, and ye gave me no meate; I was thirſtie, and ye gave me no drinke; I was a ſtranger, and ye lodged me not; I was naked, and ye clothed me not; I was ſicke, and in priſon, and ye viſited me not: in as much as ye did it not
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4863:34"/> to one of theſe little ones</hi> (ſuch a one as <hi>Ioſeph) ye did it not unto me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, were it onely the caſe of this <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, yet hee forgets the libertie which hee hath loſt, by receiving a benefit; hee forgets the greatneſſe of his obligation, by receiving ſuch a benefit, a benefit of life and well-being, which in effect hee can<note n="*" place="margin">Haneſlatis ratio at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> debitum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulat ut compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio non tantum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo aequet, ſed ut ſuperet accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum beneficium. <hi>Aq 22. 106. 6. c.</hi> Quam diu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſat minus vel aequale, non videtur facere gratis ſed reddere ouod accepit. <hi>Ibid.</hi> Potest nihilomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus retributio eſſe gratuita, ſi illud aequale aut minus tribuatur, non ut aequalitas rei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituatur ſed ut gratia referatur. <hi>Greg. de Val.</hi>
                     </note> hardly requite; hee forgets that due proportion of puniſhment which the ungratefull man deſerves, <hi>ſubſtractionem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficii</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquinas</hi>) the ſubſtraction, the taking away of that ſame benefit which hee received before, the benefit of life and well-being, by <hi>Ioſephs</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: And for this purpoſe, hee forgets the power of that God, who brings <hi>Princes to nothing, and maketh the Iudges of the Earth as vanitie, Eſay</hi> 40.23. who can ſet an <hi>Aegyptian againſt an Aegyptian,</hi> till both their names be rooted out from under Heaven; ſo that he who lives longeſt, ſhall leave nothing behinde him, but a ſpecifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Office, to aggravate the qualitie of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe: that God being the true Eagle ſtone, found in all places of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> whoſe vertue can diſcover and ſurprize all theeves and robbers of his glory, their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours right.</p>
                  <p>Nay, to ſpeake more neerely, in remembrance both of his Office and his Dreame, he forgets that his buds and bloſſomes, and Grapes and Wine, ſhall one day be turned into <hi>ſnares, and fire and brimſtone,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6.</note> 
                     <hi>and an horrible tempeſt, this ſhall be the portion of his Cup;</hi> and (which is much more than all that can be ſpoken or imagined) it will be impoſſible that ever this Cup ſhould paſſe away from him.</p>
                  <p>In a word, (beſides that incomparable, unſpeakable loſſe, <hi>He loved not bleſſing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.17.</note> 
                     <hi>therefore it ſhall be farre from him</hi>) hee forgets the depth of that bottomeleſſe Pit, wherein he ſhall be bound (never reſtored) <hi>till he hath payd the utmoſt farthing:</hi> And in the meane while, during this life, hee forgets that attractive vertue of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4863:35"/> unthankfulneſſe, which drawes the imputation of all vices upon it ſelfe, to aſſure and ratifie ſuch finall, ſuch eternall deſtruction.</p>
                  <p n="42">42 Thus you ſee, though <hi>Joſeph</hi> might well have beene preſented by the chiefe Butler as a <hi>Veſſell of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.12.</note> upon <hi>Pharaohs</hi> birth-day; yet hee is <hi>cleane for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, like a dead man out of minde, and become like a broken Veſſell;</hi> and well he may be called ſo: for as a broken Veſſell hath no ſound at all, ſo (me thinkes) he<note n="*" place="margin">Vinculorum neceſſitatem ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus ferens. <hi>Ioſeph. lib. 1. Antiq.</hi>
                     </note> opens not his mouth, though he were caſt downe, layd lower than the ground; not onely by the furious anger and partialitie of that great man, who firſt impriſoned him; but now alſo, by the neglect and unthankfulneſſe of another great man, who received ſo much obſervance from him: yet (I ſay) hee opens not his mouth, hee complaines not for want of remembrance: That ſo this <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> and all ſuch like, may know from the event, and be aſſured, though the tongue be ſilent, and perhaps will not ſpeake for the preſent; yet there is a Pen,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.1.</note> the <hi>Pen of a readie Writer,</hi> a ſacred Pen, a <hi>Pen of Iron,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.1.</note> which will write in blacke diſmall Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, and preſerve for ever the memorie of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe.</p>
                  <p n="43">43 In <hi>Ioſephs</hi> condition, you may ſee the portion of Gods children in this life; that <hi>the Race is not to the ſwift, nor the Battaile to the ſtrong, nor Bread to the wiſe, nor Riches to men of underſtanding, nor favour to men of skill,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.26.</note> 
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. And indeed <hi>Ioſeph is yet alive: Quis non carcere clauditur indigno?</hi> As there is no man, whoſe mortall body is not a priſon to his ſoule; ſo there is no Chriſtian, whoſe ſoule is not ſubject to affliction: bee hee never ſo happie, never ſo holy, yet a Dungeon is, or may bee, the place of his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation.</p>
                  <p n="44">44 In the chiefe Butlers condition, you may ſee the humour of the World, (long ſince proverbially deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the Prophet <hi>Amos) They eate the Lambes of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4863:35"/> the flocke, and the Calves out of the midſt of the Stall, they chaunt to the ſound of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ioll, and invent to themſelves Inſtruments of Muſicke, they annoint themſelves with the chiefe Ointments;</hi> and (as though this unworthineſſe of the chiefe Butler were never to be forgotten) <hi>they drinke Wine in Bowles, and are not grieved for the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Ioſeph, Amos</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. Nay, though <hi>Ioſeph</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve very much at their hands, by imploying his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, by ſpending his time, many times his fortunes, in their ſervice; though he be their owne countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nay, their kinſman according to the fleſh, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring up and downe, and ſometimes loſing himſelfe, in ſeeking after their welfare; yet, if (withall) he will not deſcend from himſelfe, and conſent to the faults of his brethren; if he will not breake the faireſt reſolutions of a free ſpirit (the ſignes of an ingenious birth and education) be of the giving hand, or (as it were) ſell himſelfe for a ſlave, to their private ends; nay further, if he will not patiently ſuffer wrong, and yet openly give thankes too, he ſhall be hated the more for his worth; falſe accuſations will be fought for, occaſions of diſpleaſure eaſily taken, and (perhaps) brotherly kindneſſe turned into the greateſt enmitie: at leaſt, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> is more likely to remaine in the Pit of affliction, or to be expoſed to the mercie of ſtrangers, (Infidels perhaps, ſuch as <hi>Iſmaelites, Aegyptians</hi>) rather than finde any favour for his kindred, or recompence for his merit, anſwerable to the Lawes of Nature and Iuſtice: ſuch is the ſtate of corruption, ſuch is the corruption of this World.</p>
                  <p n="45">45 Whereupon wee may well conclude with thoſe words of the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> in his 31. Chapter, <hi>verſe</hi> 1. <hi>Woe unto thoſe that goe downe to Aegypt for helpe:</hi> for if there be any helpe there, it is more likely to be in the Cities, than in the Villages: If in the Cities, then (me thinkes) in <hi>Zoan,</hi> the Metropolis, the chiefe Citie (as <hi>Strabo</hi> obſerves;) if in <hi>Zoan,</hi> then ſurely amongſt the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4863:36"/> 
                     <hi>Princes,</hi> the great men, the chiefe Officers: But, <hi>the Princes of Zoan are fooles, Eſay</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 11. Nay (as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in the ſame place) <hi>their wiſedome is become brutiſh:</hi> skilfull (it may be the Prophet meanes) they were in dieting brute beaſts; whereof, amongſt <hi>Aegyptians</hi> (as wee reade) men of qualitie had the charge; and no leſſe eminent, for their devotion to Dogges; <hi>Illic tota oppida canem venerantur,</hi> (ſaith the Poet) there, whole Townes, every Village inherites that diſeaſe, or (with this chiefe Butler) made famous to poſteritie for workes of uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſſe, unthankefulneſſe, or this worldly policie, which God eſteemes fooliſhneſſe: but otherwiſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving neither wiſedome, nor power, nor goodneſſe, (the neceſſarie characters of a bountifull and munificent minde) worthy to be the object of any confidence or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge in the day of trouble.</p>
                  <p>And therefore, ſince now adayes it is ſo much in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, to leane upon theſe <hi>ſtaves of broken Reedes (Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> I meane,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 36.</note> ſo called in the Prophets language) it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be too often ſpoken; <hi>Woe unto thoſe that goe downe to Aegypt for helpe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 31.</note> 
                     <hi>that truſt in Chariots, becauſe they are many; and in Horſemen, becauſe they are very ſtrong; and looke not to the holy One of Iſrael, nor ſeeke unto the Lord:</hi> for he alone is a God of compaſſion, once a fellow priſoner,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8.</note> 
                     <hi>touched with the ſenſe of our infirmities;</hi> and therefore more likely to binde up the broken-hearted, and to leade <hi>Captivitie captive:</hi> and he alone is a God of juſtice, weighing all things in a Ballance; ſo that he who gives <hi>a Cup of cold water for his ſake,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.41.</note> or receives <hi>a Prophet in the name of a Prophet,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.41.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall never want a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets reward:</hi> and he alone is <hi>the Lord, the Lord God;</hi> whoſe glory it is, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. to be <hi>gracious and mercifull, long ſuffering, and abundant in goodneſſe and truth;</hi> to heare the petitions of all them that call upon him, in his Sonnes Name: nay, his forwardneſſe to grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in ſpirituall matters, prevents the making of them: <hi>Ho, every man that thirſteth, come ye to the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4863:36"/> and he that hath no money, come buy and eate; yea, come buy Wine and Milke without money, without price, Eſay</hi> 55. <hi>v.</hi> 1. And ſhall he not, with theſe, give us all things elſe? Yes verily: For though men be ſtonie-hearted, and for the moſt part (upon like occaſions) as dumbe in effect, as thoſe Statues and Pictures whereunto <hi>Diogenes</hi> (by a choiſe kind of wiſedome) did commonly make requeſts as he paſſed by them,<note n="*" place="margin">Plut. de vitioſâ Verec.</note> 
                     <hi>ut aſſueſceret fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrari poſtulatis;</hi> that ſo, by inuring and acquainting himſelfe with theſe ſpeechleſſe denyals, hee might the better teach others, not to hope for much, to promiſe themſelves little, to build upon nothing, to beare all croſſes with a quiet minde; and in particular, to deride and ſcoffe at the language of the Beaſt, which in theſe extremities heares and ſees, and ſayes nothing: Yet if wee patiently abide Gods leyſure, if wee commit our wayes to him, and wait upon the wiſedome of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed times,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.7.</note> 
                     <hi>he will remember David and all his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> bring <hi>his ſoule out of priſon, and helpe them to right, who ſuffer wrong.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, though the <hi>Dungeon</hi> be like the <hi>Sepulchre, wherein never man lay before</hi> for ſuch offences, offences (indeed) of others, his accuſers, not of his owne; though Oppreſſion ſet a watch upon the doores, and be it ſelfe a Rock of Stone, to keepe both them from being opened, and the priſoner from riſing againe: yet, as one day, an Angell of God, a miniſtring Spirit, ſhall deſcend from Heaven to viſit this Dungeon, to open theſe doores, to juſtifie a good cauſe, and to make it ſhine as bright as himſelfe, and that for feare of him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.4.</note> 
                     <hi>the Keepers</hi> (the wretched Keepers) <hi>will ſhake, and become as dead men;</hi> ſo, in this life,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> the ſame God hath ordained <hi>a Lanthorne for his annointed, and a Light for his ſteps,</hi> powerfull meanes to diſcover the wayes of darkeneſſe, and to ſtill <hi>the voice of the oppreſſor:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob</hi> 3.18.</note> whereby (no doubt) according to his promiſe, and the caſe of temporall happineſſe, he will <hi>raiſe the poore out of the dust,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.6, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>that he may ſet him
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4863:37"/> with Princes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.17.</note> 
                     <hi>even the Princes of his people; he will decke his Prieſts with health,</hi> and <hi>his Saints ſhall rejoice and ſing:</hi> and all this now, as heretofore, by great Courtiers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of bleſſed memorie; amongſt whom, though the chiefe Butler (being entreated and engaged too) would not ſpeake for <hi>Ioſeph, a poore man, a Prieſt, a Saint;</hi> yet one,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.</note> partly of his profeſſion, good <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer to <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> (notwithſtanding the fruition and honour of his place) will looke <hi>ſadly,</hi> and of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe make requeſt to the King, that <hi>he may goe build up the walls of Jeruſalem,</hi> and comfort his afflicted brethren.</p>
                  <p>More particularly, God will (as hee did) give <hi>Ioſeph wiſedome and favour</hi> in the ſight of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 7.10.</note> a moſt juſt, provident, gratefull, bountifull Prince: nay, he can draw water out of a <hi>ſtonie Rocke,</hi> and that by the hand of this chiefe Butler; cauſing him (though a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull wretch) to make mention of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> even then (when like a weake Politician, befooled with covetouſneſſe, or ſelfe-conceit, intending altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his owne) he ſhall effect onely <hi>Ioſephs</hi> promotion, and himſelfe never after ſo much as named againe, when <hi>Ioſeph</hi> came in place, but requited in his owne kinde, <hi>not remembred, cleane forgot:</hi> and no mervaile; for hee who makes another man eate the <hi>Bread of carefulneſſe,</hi> doth well deſerve himſelfe to drinke a draught of <hi>deadly Wine,</hi> a Cup of finall indignation.</p>
                  <p n="46">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.9.</note>46 In a word, to conclude all, he can turne this <hi>Water</hi> into <hi>Wine</hi> (as hee did at a Marriage) making <hi>all things worke together for the beſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> 
                     <hi>to thoſe who love him:</hi> But wee know hee hath reſerved the <hi>beſt Wine till the laſt;</hi> that then whoſoever drinketh, may <hi>never thirſt againe,</hi> and ſtand in need of any Courtiers kindneſſe; that time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Feaſt of a great King (greater than <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) the King of Kings; and that no birth-day, but the <hi>Marriage Supper</hi> of his onely begotten, onely beloved Sonne: At which moſt glorious ſolemnitie, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (no queſtion,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4863:37"/> amongſt others) will be cloathed with a <hi>Wedding Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> even that Robe of Innocence,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.12.</note> which hee left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him; and being found a <hi>wiſe Virgin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</note> having <hi>Oyle</hi> in his <hi>Lampe,</hi> burning and ſhining in the midſt of a darke Dungeon, ſhall from thence enter with the <hi>Bridegroome</hi> into his Chamber of Preſence, that Imperiall Seat of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Majeſtie, there to reigne with him for evermore.</p>
                  <p>Vnto which Kingdome, the Lord of his infinite mercie bring us all, for his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus ſake: To whom, with the Father, and the Holy-Ghoſt, be aſcribed all honour, prayſe, power, and Dominion, now and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="approbation">
            <head>Novemb. 22. 1634.</head>
            <p>PErlegi has duas conciones Magiſtri <hi>Thornton,</hi> quae continent folia manuſcripta <hi>35.</hi> aut circiter, in quibus nihil reperio ſanae Doctrinae aut bonis mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus contrarium, quo minus cum utilitate publica im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primi poſſint, ſub ea tamen conditione, ut ſi non intra ſex menſes typis mandentur, haec licentia ſit omnino irrita.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>GVILIELMVS HAYWOOD,</hi> Capell. Dom. Archiep. Cant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
